<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers set in their true light in order to give the nations a clear sight of what they hold concerning Jesus of Nazareth, the Scripture, water baptism, the Lords Supper, magistracy, ministry laws and government / historically collected out of their most approved authors, which are their best continuing books from the year of their rise, 1650 to the year of their progress 1696 by Francis Bugg, senior.</title>
            <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10831442</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10831442</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46060</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46060)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1417:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers set in their true light in order to give the nations a clear sight of what they hold concerning Jesus of Nazareth, the Scripture, water baptism, the Lords Supper, magistracy, ministry laws and government / historically collected out of their most approved authors, which are their best continuing books from the year of their rise, 1650 to the year of their progress 1696 by Francis Bugg, senior.</title>
                  <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and are to be sold by J. Brome and J. Guillim,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A brief history of Quakerism.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  History.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46060:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46060:1"/>
            <p>THE QUAKERS <hi>Set in their true Light,</hi> In order to give the Nations A Clear SIGHT.</p>
            <p>Of what they hold concerning <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> the Scriptures, Water Baptiſm, the Lords Supper, Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Laws, and Government.</p>
            <p>HISTORICALLY COLLECTED Out of their moſt approved Authors, which are their beſt Conſtruing books, from the year of their Riſe 1650, to the year of their Progreſs 1696.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> Senior.</p>
            <q>But evil men and Seducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived; For as Jannes and Jambres with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Moſes, ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the truth: Men of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith; whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped, who ſubvert whole houſholds; but they ſhall proceed no farther, for their folly ſhall be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt unto all men. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3.8, 9, 13. Titus 3.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>C. Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>J. Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:46060:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46060:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND HENRY, L. Biſhop of London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Humbly conceive it my duty to diſcover to your Lordſhip what I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend may be of dangerous conſequence either to Church or State: And this emboldens me to offer the enſuing diſcourſe to your Lordſhips pious conſideration. I muſt humbly confeſs 'tis a great preſumption upon your Honours Patience and Patronage: But that which (amongſt other things) gives me encouragement hereunto, and which I hape may plead my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, at leaſt extenuate my offence, is the Quakers frequent Dedications and Preſentations of their Books to the King, Lords and Commons, and other Magiſtrates, from year to year, one Seſſions of Parliament after another, for thirty or forty years together, beſeeching, begging, and craving their aid, ſupport and authority; whilſt in their Books to their Diſciples they utterly diſclaim any ſuch ſeeking to outward authority: But inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when not ſuiting their Intereſt they'll Impeach and Condemn their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding as Antichriſtian, and Arraign, Try and Condemn the Learned Proteſtant Clergy, as inconſiſtent to Chriſtianity. Thus, like the Cameli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they can turn themſelves into all colours, their Books being of two ſorts, carrying two different faces: And it was by this method that the <hi>Arians</hi> of old deceived the Emperor <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> who at laſt made Laws in their behalf, againſt the Orthodox. And that this is no new Artifice your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may obſerve from the book of <hi>Exodus;</hi> that notwithſtanding <hi>Moſes</hi> was divinely inſpired and gifted witb Miracles to confirm his Commiſſion, yet the Magicians by their Magick Act and cunning Intreagues came very near him in ſhew: likewiſe <hi>Simon Magus, Acts 8.</hi> by his Sorcery and
<pb facs="tcp:46060:3"/> Juggling Tricks, ſo bewitched the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that they gave great heed to all he ſaid. And Hiſtory ſufficiently informs us what hard work the Proteſtants had to confute the Papiſts, whoſe Books were like the Quakers, of two ſorts, profeſſing in one ſort, what they utterly rejected in the other ſort: And this made Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in his <hi>Defence to the Apology,</hi> &amp;c. propoſe to his Reader, viz. <hi>Good Reader, if thou wilt examine our doings, I beſeech thee ſearch and prove what hath been wrote on both ſides, and do not ſuffer thy ſelf by ſhews and ſhifts to be beguiled, for what man will ſeem to deal ſo uprightly as a Juggler; he will ſtrike up his ſleeves, make bare his arms, and open his hands and fingers, and bid thee behold: And thou wilt think him to be a good plain man, and marvel thou ſhouldſt poſſibly be deceived, and yet indeed his whole deſign is nothing but to deceive thee: and the more ſimply and plainly he would ſeem to deal, ſo much the more he will deceive thee, otherwiſe he were no Juggler,</hi> &amp;c. And to this agrees that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſaying of <hi>Ireneaeus,</hi> in his third Book againſt Hereticks, viz. <hi>Whilſt Heretick ſpeak like the faithful, they not only mean otherwiſe than what they ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> clean contrary: And by their Tenents, full of Blaſphemy, they deſtroy the Souls of thoſe, who with their fair words ſuck in the poyſon of their foul opinions.</hi> And no marvel (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of Light; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no great th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng if his Miniſters alſo be transformed as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works, <hi>2 Cor. 13.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, my Lord, being ſenſible of the Quakers method, not only of their unw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y'd ſollicitation of the Members of Parliament, both Lords and Commons, for many years; but alſo in ſending their Books into all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Shires, Cities, Towns and Villages in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> as well as parts beyond the Seas, I thought it my duty to let the World know their principles from their Printed Books: For, as ſimple as they look, and as innocent as they ſeem to appear, for deep ſubtilty they outſtrip both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Jeſuit;</hi> and notwithſtanding their many and great pretences to meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> charity, and long-ſuffering, there is not a more uncharitable and cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people under heaven. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's moſt humble and obedient Servant,</hi> Fr. Bugg.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46060:3"/>
               <head>An Apologetical Introduction to the Hiſtory of the Riſe, Growth, and Progreſs of <hi>QUAKERISM.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF <hi>Athanaſius</hi> made an Apology for his writing againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> and other of late for their expoſing the errors of the <hi>Socinians;</hi> nay, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> thought herſelf oblig'd to Apologize (in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) for writing againſt the errors of the Papiſts; 'tis but reaſonable for me to think myſelf under the ſame Obligation for writing againſt the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous errors of the Quakers; for ſurely there has not appeared a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Monſter upon the Stage ſince the days of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> than <hi>George Fox</hi> was in his day; nor did <hi>Simon Magus</hi> more applaud himſelf, nor more of his Followers adore him; nor take greater care to continue the Memory of him, than the Quakers have done of <hi>G. Fox,</hi> witneſs the reprint of his Labours, his Travels, his Miracles and Wonders: Inſomuch, that what many Ages have perplexed the Church withal ſingly, we are aſſaulted with at once; as if the ſcattered Limbs of Hereſy had rallied and reinforced themſelves for a freſh Battle. I have ſeen <hi>Muggleton</hi>'s <hi>Tranſcendent Spiritual Treatiſe, &amp;c.</hi> and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find that he holds pace with <hi>George Fox</hi> in his Books, <hi>Truths Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sauls Errand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>A Threefold Eſtate of Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. and divers other Books wrote formerly, and which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ill own commend, and recommend to their Diſciples, as Books wrote by divine Authority, yea from the Eternal Spirit, and Power of God; ſee Sect. the XVI. Nay, in many things <hi>Muggle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and the Quakers ſeem to be Twins: For <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſays, 'tis not lawful to fight with a Sword of Steel, ſo ſay the Quakers; at leaſt until they get power into their hands, as in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> where they can both fight with a Carnal Sword, fine, impriſon, and perſecute their Brethren, as the Trial of <hi>G. Keith,</hi> and others, ſets forth at large. <hi>Muggleton</hi> denies the Bleſſed Trinity, ſo do the Quakers; ſee <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s <hi>Sandy Foundation Shaken,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Muggleton</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth the Scriptures, in compariſon of his own Writings, ſo do the Quakers; ſee Sect. the XVI. and XVIII. <hi>Muggleton</hi> pretends to know any thing, ſo do the Quakers, who ſay, <hi>We have a Spirit given to us beyond all the Fore-fathers ſince the Apoſtles day: and we can diſcern who are Saints, who are Devils, and who are Apoſtates, without ſpeaking ever a word,</hi> G. Fox<hi>'s Gr. Miſt.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 89. And again, <q>We need none to give us diſcerning or judgment, Chriſt hath furniſhed us already, and doth on all occaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <bibl> 
                        <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 58. </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <hi>Muggletons</hi> Diſciples adore him as an excellent Prophet, ſo do the Quakers adore <hi>G. Fox,</hi> ſee Sect. V. <hi>Muggleton</hi> is greatly given to curſe and damn ſuch as receive not his Meſſage, ſo do the Quakers; read their Books before named: Only for a Taſte I may recite a few of <hi>G. Fox</hi> his words to Mr. <hi>Calmfeild</hi> a Miniſter, in their Book, <hi>Truths Defence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>Thou painted Beaſt, thou art damned openly; I charge thee to be a Witch, and bewitch the People: Brazen-fac'd thou art, for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46060:4"/> thou art a Beaſt, thou blind Sot; for Deſtruction thou art ordained to go therein, and the Lake that burneth, and the Pit thou art to be turned into eternally: No Prayer can we ſend to thee but for thy Deſtruction; thou art a Serpent, thou Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition, a Child of the Devil, an Enemy of all Righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with abundance more of the like tendency lye diſperſedly in the ſaid Book.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all that can be quoted out of their Books which juſtly render them Antichriſtian, Antiſcriptural, and Antimagiſtratical, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they have many Advocates, and ſome Arguments, as well as the <hi>Arians, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, &amp;c.</hi> And the ſame cauſe move to the ſame thing, and this move me to Apologize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For altho I am ſhort of the gifts and parts of thoſe who wrote againſt the aforeſaid Errors (and for which they thought themſelves obliged to Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gize) yet I do believe, that as we are Chriſtians, we ought to contend for the Faith once delivered to the Saints; and my Conſcience beareth me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I have endeavoured to defend the cauſe of the ſame truth, with the ſame purpoſe, and by the ſame principles, ſo far forth as I am capable; and that it may appear ſuch I ſhall anſwer ſome objections.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Fra. Bugg,</hi> ſay the Quakers, endeavours to render us odious.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That his Printed Sheet delivered to the Houſe of Commons was mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That his impeaching our yearly Meeting was preſumptuous.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That great part of what he writ is not of his own doing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> Fr. Bugg, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to render the Quakers odious and obnoxious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I moſt ſolemnly deny that my end in writing againſt them is to render them odious; but to convince them of their erroneous Principles and Practices, to warn others to take heed of them: And this cannot be done without ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they hold, nor better than from their own conſtruing Book; and that this is my way I appeal to the Chriſtian Reader. Nay, further I have from time to time endeavoured to prevail with their Teachers to retract their errors, and condemn their moſt blaſphemous books, upon which I ſhould have gladly deſiſted; and ſince I begun this Book, I ſent a Letter to <hi>G. W.</hi> to let him know that if he would meet me according to his propoſals in his printed ſheet, intituled <hi>The Quak. Vind. &amp;c.</hi> delivered to the Parliament, that I would deſiſt: giving him ten days time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But no anſwer returned I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed: And let them not blame me for expoſing their errors and pernicious principles, ſince they are too proud to retract and condemn them: And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al let them remember, that notwithſtanding the Proverb, 'tis a greater crime to ſteal a Horſe than to look on, unleſs the ſtander by conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that 'tis worſe in you to hold theſe Errors, to write theſe Books, to juſtifie theſe Blaſphemies, than for me to recite them, and lay them open to publick view: So that 'tis a web of your own weaving that I cover you withal, how fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſoever you look: beſides, if you look into your Book, ſtiled, <hi>Plain and peaceable Advice to Presbyterians, &amp;c.</hi> p. 1. you tell them, <q>That their principle was to fight for their Religion, and to promote the ſame by the power of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46060:4"/> the Sword, and that their Miniſters always laboured to perſwade them to it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And at that juncture of time too, when there was great talk of a Presbyterian Plot. Again, ſee your Anſwer to <hi>John Faldo,</hi> p. 109. "And why poor Nonconformiſts after all their preacht up Battels, Spoils, Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Sacrileges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 119. Here are true Goſpel Miniſters, whoſe Goſpel is peace on earth, and good will towards men; and not garments rolled in the Blood of Kings, Princes, Rulers, and People; no worldly Armies, Battles, Victories, Trophies, Spoils, Sequeſtration, Decimations, and the like blood-thirſty and tyrannical projects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And yet at the ſame time when the Presbyterians were engaged as the Quakers would inſinuate; none preached up Battles, Murther, and Slaughter more than the Quakers, as I could ſhew at large, but chuſe rather to refer the Reader to <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But why do they talk of expoſing; who ever expoſed, nay who ever ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and belied their Adverſaries, both in words, writing, and printing, more than the Quakers have done? who ever called the Publick Miniſters, Witches, Devils, Blaſphemers, falſe Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as they have done. And this was the War <hi>Edw. Burrows</hi> talked, and by which they began, ſee his Epiſt. to <hi>G. Fox</hi> his <hi>Gr. Myſt.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>And firſt of all our mouths were opened, and our ſpirit filled with indignation againſt the Prieſts and Teachers, and againſt them we firſt began to war, as being the Cauſers of the people to err; yea the fountain of all wickedneſs, the iſſue of prophaneneſs, the Antichriſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this was (ſays <hi>Burrows</hi>) the firſt work we entered upon, to threſh down the deceivers, and to lay them open, that all people might ſee their ſhame, and turn from them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Come <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> let us turn the Scales, and try if you can be willing to be dealt by as you have dealt by others, and whether you can freely drink (drink it you muſt whether you will or no) the ſame Cup that you have plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully poured out to others: you began with the Clergy, and I begin with the Quakers; your mouth was open, and your ſpirit filled with indignation againſt the Clergy, becauſe they preached out of the Scripture, called Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the Lords Supper Ordinances of Chriſt; and <hi>my mouth is open,</hi> (to uſe your phraſe) <hi>and my Spirit is filled wieh indignation</hi> againſt the Quakers contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture, profaning the Ordinances, and Idolizing each other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your firſt work you entered upon was to threſh down the Clergy, as the fountain of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, the iſſue of prophaneneſs, and the deceivers of the Nation; and to lay them open, that all people might ſee their ſhame, and turn from them:</hi> And now my work I am entered upon is <hi>to threſh down Quakeriſm,</hi> as the peſt of the Nation, <hi>the fountain of wickedneſs, the iſſue of prophaneneſs, the deceivers of the people,</hi> and the broachers of damnable hereſies, and to lay them open, that all people may ſee your ſhame, and in abhorrence of your abomination to turn from you. Come <hi>G. W.</hi> look for the ſame meaſure, for you are like to have it heaped, thruſt down, and running over. Come <hi>George</hi> remember your Brother <hi>Pen,</hi> who in his Book, <hi>The Skirmiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, &amp;c.</hi> being told <hi>that the womb of Iniquity was in the Quakers Writings,</hi> ſaid p. 10. <q>He has invaded my body and ſoul, religion and life: for I am (<hi>ſaid</hi> W. Pen)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46060:5"/> by my doctrine, if the Prieſt may be believed, an Heretick, a Blaſphemer, an Atheiſt, &amp;c. And what remains but that the Dogs or the Lyons devour me, the Rabble or the Government ſacrifice me, &amp;c.</q> And I pray, good Mr <hi>Pen,</hi> what are the Prieſts, if the Quakers may be believed, are they not <hi>Witches, Devils, Blaſphemers, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, if what you ſay may be credited, what are they good for, but <hi>the Dogs or Lions to tear them to pieces, the Rabble and the Government to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them,</hi> ſaying there ☞ goes a Witch, read <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.18. which ſays 'tis death: here ☞ goes a Blaſphemer, ſtone him to death, <hi>Lev.</hi> 24.16. Here goes a falſe Prophet, who is not to live, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.20. knock him down: thus in every Town where you come to get credit, you have invaded their Soul and Body, Religion and Life: Come ſmooth <hi>G. W.</hi> is not this ſeditious in the nature of it? You know <hi>Weſtmorland Petitioners</hi> told you ſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That my ſhéet delivered to the Houſe of Commons,</hi> Dec. 1693. <hi>was mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Reader, I will give you ſome account of the reaſon of it. I having occaſion to attend the Parliament by way of ſollicitation about our Trade, 1693. there was every day 4 or 5 Quakers up and down attending alſo; at laſt they preſented a fine ſmooth printed paper, ſtiled <hi>The Caſe of the People called Quakers humbly offered to the tender Conſideration of the Houſe of Commons, to incline them to grant the Petition of the ſaid People,</hi> &amp;c. The Petition was to have their Word paſs for an Oath, that they might be Rivals with the Peers of the Realm. But when I ſaw it, and conſidered how they but a little before had indicted me for printing a Book unlicenced, when I was 60 miles off, and they got them ſeized, and taken from my Bookſeller; notwithſtanding they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently print and publiſh without Licence: and alſo conſidering how by little and little they are getting ground, and knowing what a litigious People they would be, if there was not that Barr to keep them out of Government, I took their printed fine wheedling ſheet, and anſwered it; and did immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately deliver the Anſwer to it to the Members, as I think it was my duty; and it was as kindly accepted by the Members: and the very ſame day, I delivered my ſaid Anſwer to their Caſe their Petition was thrown out, to the great joy of all Chriſtian People; and notwithſtanding <hi>G. W.</hi>'s belying Mr. <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> I had his leave and hearty aſcent to deliver it, and never had of him a word of diſlike for all I have writ, nor of none ſuch as he was.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That my Impeaching their yearly méeting was preſumptuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If ſo? But why then did you teach me the way: See <hi>Burroughs works,</hi> printed by the order and approbation of <hi>Geo. Whitehead, Anno</hi> 1672. p. 793. ſtiled, <hi>Perſecution Impeached as a Traytor againſt God.</hi> Now all your wilful ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for your obſtinate diſobedience to the Laws of the Land, by you are called Perſecution, and that you have the preſumption to Impeach all the Judges, Juſtices, and Inferiour Officers, under the odious Name of Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why may not I for once. Impeach you who ſit at <hi>Devonſhire-houſe,</hi> to null, make void, and repeal as unlawful, what the King, Lords and Commons, make lawful at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> And whether I be moſt preſumptuous for telling you of your faults, or you in committing them (for that's the great caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46060:5"/> you and me) I will leave the Reader to judge, when I have recited the ſaid Impeachment and Proof, as in the ſaid ſheet, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="impeachment">
                  <head>The IMPEACHMENT.</head>
                  <p>That <hi>Geo. White</hi> and his Brethren, at a Convocation at <hi>London,</hi> the 5th of <hi>May, 1693.</hi> ending the 8th day of the ſame month, did contrive, make, and promulgate ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical, containing in them divers matters and things, contrary to the Laws and Statutes of the Realm, againſt the Rights of Parliament, againſt the property of the ſubject, and matters tending to Sedition, and of dangerous conſequence; as may appear by the recited Epiſtle. A few inſtances thereof as proof, I ſhall recite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proof">
                  <head>The IMPEACHMENT PROVED.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Quak. Yearly Epiſt. 1693. p. 1.</hi> And therefore that all due care be taken againſt the <hi>Grand Oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Youk</hi> of <hi>Tythes,</hi> that our Chriſtian Teſtimony born and greatly ſuffered for be faithfully maintained againſt <hi>them</hi> in <hi>all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,</hi> and againſt <hi>Steeplehouſe Rates,</hi> as alſo againſt the Burthen and Impoſition of <hi>Oaths;</hi> that Friends, at all their monthly and quarterly Meetings, be reminded to call for the Records of the Sufferings of Friends, to ſee that they be duly gathered, truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and kept; and accordingly ſent up [to <hi>London</hi>] as hath been often adviſed, both of what Tyths, <hi>&amp;c</hi> pretended to be due: and for how long a time, and the time when taken; and by, and for whom; and what Goods are taken, and the value thereof; as well of thoſe not exceeding, as thoſe exceeding the ſums or quantities [of Tythes] demanded (it being a ſuffering in both for truth ſake) they being in theſe particulars found defective and imperfect in divers Counties, which is an obſtruction to the <hi>General Record</hi> of Friends Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="observation">
                     <head>Obſervation.</head>
                     <p>From whence we may conclude, that the main reaſon why the Quakers refuſe to pay their Tyths and Church Rates, and other things which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment calls for at their hands, is the Authority of their Yearly Meetings, and not Scripture Proof; and where is there a Pariſh in <hi>England,</hi> but feel (more or leſs) the ſad effects and evil conſequences of theſe their Antima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratical Incroachments; beſides it looks very ill and ungrateful to charge the Government with Perſecution for Tythes, which is a civil right eſtabliſhed by Law. Yea even in that very Act of Parliament which gave them their Tolleration; and which ſome, if not all theſe Anti-Lawmakers know well enough, 'tis in <hi>fol.</hi> 308. thus,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Provided always that nothing herein contained ſhall be conſtrued to exempt any of the perſons aforeſaid from paying of Tythes, or other Parochial Duties, or any other Duties, to the Church or Miniſter; or from any Proſecution in any Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Court, or elſewhere for the ſame.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:46060:6"/>
                     <p>And I knowing theſe things, and conſidering their calling part of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments proceedings in the very ſame Act of Parliament <hi>grand oppreſſion,</hi> yea <hi>an Antichriſtian Yoak of Bondage,</hi> and, as ſuch, warn their Diſciples not to pay them; thereby acquitting and abſolving the Kings Subjects (if the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers be ſuch) from their active obedience to the Laws of the Land; and which is ſtill worſe, to cauſe them to bring up to <hi>London</hi> a true and perfect Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of all and ſingular the diſtreſſes taken for their non-payment of Tythes, Church-Wardens Rates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this diſobedience is in a great part owing to the uſurpation of this Anti-magiſtratical Synod or Convocation: Nor is this all, but if their yearly Epiſtles (which they keep as cloſe as poſſibly they can) were all ſeen, you would ſee a hundred Inſtances of the like kind; one more I may ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi> In the 22d Year of King <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d, there was an Act of Parliament made to prevent ſeditious Conventicles, and that no Meetings above the number of four, beſides the Family, were to beheld under pretence of Religious Worſhip in other manner than according to the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But in direct oppoſition to this, the Quakers made a Law at their Yearly Meeting, or Convocation held at <hi>Devonſhire</hi> Houſe the 27th of <hi>May</hi> 1675, <hi>viz. So it is our Advice and Judgment, that all Friends Gathered in the Name of Jeſus keep up thoſe publick Teſtimonies (meaning their Meetings in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective places) and not <hi>decline, forſake,</hi> or <hi>remove</hi> their Publick Aſſemblies, becauſe of times of ſufferings, as worldly, fearful, and politick Profeſſors have done (meaning the Presbyterians, Independants and Baptiſts) becauſe of Informers, and the like Perſecutors.</hi> Signed <hi>per G. Whitehead, William Pen, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whereby it may be ſeen that their Principles and Doctrine are Anti-magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratical and Unſcriptural too, for ſaid Chriſt, <hi>If they perſecute thee in one City flee to the next.</hi> And his Deſciples met privately for fear of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as more largely handled in my Book, <hi>The Painted Harlot both ſtript and whipt,</hi> &amp;c. Thus much by way of Apology for my Impeaching the Quakers preſumptuous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in their Synodical Aſſembly.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>That what I have wrote hithetto, or great part of it, is not of my own doing but by the Aſſiſtance of Learned Perſons.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I know it has been the way and manner of the Quakers, from the firſt day I wrote againſt their Errors, to uſe all the ways and means they can to blaſt my endeavours, and by lies and falſe inſinuations to weaken my Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony: ſometimes I write (ſay they) like a Fool, a Boy of 11 Years of Age will laugh at it; when that will not do, then I write ſo much otherwiſe that it cannot be my own; but ſome of the wicked Prieſts (as they account the Clergy) help me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this being bruted abroad, ſeveral Gentlemen have deſired me to give ſome account thereof, which is as follows.</p>
                     <p>When <hi>G. W.</hi> in his charitable Eſſay, <hi>p.</hi> 2. charged me with <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Why did not thy Miniſter ſtop thee from running into ſuch Socinianiſm,</hi> &amp;c. I went to Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> our Miniſter, and ſhewed him the paſſage, and deſired his aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance all anſwering that particular. He read <hi>Whitehead</hi> s <hi>Eſſay,</hi> and my Book to which his was pretended to be an Anſwer, and he told me that what I had wrote was found; and he immediately took his Pen, and wrote part of the 3d
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46060:6"/> and 4th pages in the Introduction of <hi>New Rome Arraigned,</hi> &amp;c. And which I alſo in the ſame page acknowledge in theſe words, <hi>And this my Miniſter tells me is not Ignorance nor Socinianiſm; but your Books teach it, &amp;c.</hi> And except this, I do not know that ever I had any Clergyman or other Scholar by me an hour in all I have wrote; nor ſix lines added or diminiſhed by any ſuch a one, nor has any Man ſo much as ſeen this before I ſent it to <hi>London</hi> for the Preſs. I do ſay that my Book, <hi>New Rome Unm. &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>New Rome Arraigned, &amp;c.</hi> I did ſhow to Mr. <hi>Archer,</hi> and to another neighbouring Miniſter a very worthy and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſon, in Manuſcript; and both of them might alter here and there a word, which in the whole, in both Books, might contain 3 or 4 lines; but they altered no matter neither by adding or diminiſhing, but very well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of what I had done, conſidering my capacity, as to Learning, and my buſineſs as a Tradeſman. But what if I had aſſiſtance I am not the firſt, better men than I am, and fitter for ſuch work, have had aſſiſtance. I could, if it were for my preſent purpoſe ſhew, that the very Quakers, who pretend they write by the Eternal Spirit immediately from Heaven, they not only have aſſiſtance, but when their Books come at their ſecond days Meeting in <hi>London</hi> for Approbation, they then will take out, and put to, what is ſaid to be thus wrote in the Name of the Lord, which is a moſt horrible cheat, for their meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſo wrote is either ſo, or not ſo; if ſo, how unfaithful are theſe Seers to alter what was given forth in the Name of the Lord; if not, ſee what Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors are theſe Elders to approve of what they believe is falſe: And yet how frequent is it with their Quaker Teachers to queſtion the truth of all mens ſincerity but their own; charging the Clergy to be Falſe Prophets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now I do challenge <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. P.</hi> to produce one Clergy-man in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ever propheſied in the Name of the Lord, and the thing came ot to paſs. But <hi>G. W.</hi> and <hi>W. Pen</hi> know, that 'tis frequent with their Preachers ſo to propheſy, and are found falſe Prophets, in that the thing comes not to paſs, witneſs <hi>Sol. Eccles</hi> who propheſied, that <hi>John Story</hi> ſhould dye within a year, he being at that time ill, yet it pleaſed God he lived about 4 years after. But why ſhould they render me ſuch an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> as that I ſhould not be able to deal with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are not ſuch Conjurers themſelves: I know they did not always account me ſo, when they choſe me to be their Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to go to the <hi>London</hi> meeting about Sufferings, about the year 1670. Nor when I was Clerk to their monthly and quarterly meetings 16 or 18 years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: Nor when they had their Regiſter-book to new model, and to add <hi>Ely</hi> ſufferings to it; (which old Records being by me, ſerve to ſhew me ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Intrigues, particularly <hi>Sam. Cater</hi>'s ſham-ſuffering, for preaching at <hi>Plakenham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> (where, pretending he loſt 20 <hi>l.</hi> yet got 10 <hi>l.</hi> clear by it) See Sect. 17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as this Licence ſhews, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fra. Bugg <hi>we deſire thee to draw out the ſufferings out of the monthly Book, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord them in the Publick Regiſter-books, and add</hi> Ely <hi>and</hi> Littleport <hi>ſufferings to the reſt. Let them be done carefully and ſpeedily, it being by our Aſſent,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Robert Smith, Rob. Letchworth, Jeremy Roſe, Joſeph Nun, Edw. Wingfeild, Robert Barber.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus much by way of Introduction.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Mildenhall,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 15. 1695.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>FRANCIS BUGG,</hi> Sen.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:46060:7"/>
               <head>A Brief HISTORY of the Riſe, Growth, and Progreſs of <hi>QUAKERISM.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION I.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt riſe of <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> was in the year 1650. For <hi>George Fox</hi> coming to <hi>Derby,</hi> and going into the Church to diſturb the Miniſter, was by the Juſtices committed to Priſon, for that and his other blaſphemous principles; and to this agree <hi>Edw. Burrough</hi>'s Epiſtle on the front of <hi>Geo. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Miſt. &amp;c.</hi> And this Juſtice <hi>Bennet</hi> was the firſt that ever call'd them <hi>Quakers:</hi> This I can prove by other Books, but you may read it in <hi>Geo. Fox</hi>'s <hi>Journal, p.</hi> 32. to 40. And that it may plainly appear with what principles the <hi>Quakers</hi> came into the world withal at their firſt entrance, you may read a Copy of the Warrant, by which they were juſtly impriſoned, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>
                              <hi>To the Maſter of the Houſe of Correction in <hi>Derby.</hi>
                              </hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>We have here ſent you the Bodies of <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> and <hi>John Fretwell,</hi> brought before us this day, and charged with the avowing, uttering and broaching divers blaſphemous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which upon their examination before as they have confeſſed: Theſe are therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you forthwith upon ſight hereof, to receive them the ſaid <hi>G. Fox</hi> and <hi>J. Fretwell</hi> into your Cuſtody, and them therein ſafely to keep, during the ſpace of ſix months, without Bail or Mainprize, or until they ſhall find ſufficient ſecurity to be of the good behaviour, or be thence delivered by order from our ſelves. Hereof you are not to fail.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under our Hands and Seals <date>this thirtieth day of <hi>October, 1650.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ger. Bennet.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Nath. Barton.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>I was once minded to have ſet forth more particularly what principles they came into the world withal, as I find them, even by the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves, put forth in a Book ſtiled <hi>Saul's Errand to Damaſcus, p:</hi> 1, 2. which, tho they have in the ſame Book pretended to anſwer the ſaid Petition, yet I do poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirm that their ſaid Anſwer looks more like a Confeſſion than a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Denyal: As alſo the ſaid Petition and their pretended Anſwer, being, with other their Time-ſerving Treacherous principles, fully ſpoken to, in that excellent Book lately put forth by a Divine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> entituled, <hi>The Snake in the Graſs; or Satan transformed into an Angel of Light: Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the deep and <hi>unſuſpected ſubtilty,</hi> couched under the <hi>pretended ſimplicity</hi> of the principal Leaders of the Quakers,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the Weſt End of St <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1696. containing about 600 pages; inſomuch that ſhould I write after him, to ſhew their facing about to every power, even as the Weather-cock, ſometimes for the Parliament, ſometimes for the Rump, ſometimes for the Committee of Safety, ſometimes for the Council of State, and then for Monarchy; and to ſhew their encouraging <hi>Oliver</hi> againſt the Royal party, it would be like lighting a candle at noon-day: Their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46060:7"/> being ſo excellently ſet forth in the ſaid Book, yet that the World may ſee with what principles they preſt into the world, againſt all Rule, Law and Government, I may tranſcribe the ſaid principles; becauſe by what follows it may be ſeen what foundation they went upon, which was under pretence of magnifying the Light in themſelves, to deny Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value his death and ſufferings, contemn his Laws contained in the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, deſpiſe his Ordinances, revile Magiſtrates, reproach Miniſters: In a word, they not only by theſe principles hereto annexed, but by their whole proceedings, have not only verified what I have already ſaid, but manifeſted their principles to be Antiſcriptural, Antimagiſtratical, Antichriſtian, unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and irreligious. An Abſtract of the ſaid Petition is as followeth. <hi>Saul's Errand to Damaſcus, &amp;c. p.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>To the Right Honorable the Council of State, the Humble Petition of ſeveral Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Juſtices of the Peace, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and People within the County of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                        <p>THat <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> and <hi>James Nailer</hi> are perſons diſaffected to Religion, and the wholſom Laws of this Nation, who have broached opinions, tending to the deſtruction of the Relation of Subjects to their Magiſtrates, Wives to their Husbands, Children to their Parents, Servants to their Maſters, Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to their Miniſters; particularly,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> profeſſed that he was equal with God.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. He profeſſed himſelf to be the eternal Judge of the World: (meaning the Light in him.)</p>
                        <p n="3">3. He ſaid he was the Judge of the World: (ſtill with the ſame <hi>Inuendo</hi> I ſuppoſe.)</p>
                        <p n="4">4. He ſaid he was the Chriſt, the Way, the Truth, and the Life: (ſtill meaning the Light: This I can prove from his Writings extant amongſt the Quakers.)</p>
                        <p n="5">5. He ſaid, that whoever took a place of Scripture and preached from it was a Conjurer, and his preaching Conjuration: (this is frequent in the Quakers Books, yea, an approved piece of Doctrine.)</p>
                        <p n="6">6. He ſaid the Scripture was Carnal: (yea, Death, Duſt, Serpents meat, Beaſtly ware, the Husk; this <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> hath vindicated.)</p>
                        <p>Thus much reſpecting <hi>Geo. Fox:</hi> what is relating to <hi>Ja. Nailer</hi> is ſpoken to in the recited Book, <hi>The Snake, &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>G. Fox</hi> being their great Apoſtle, and the founder of Quakeriſm, I was willing to ſet down the principles upon which he ſet up, and for which he was impriſoned, as you ſee: And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> and his followers have publiſhed a Journal of his Noble and Ignoble acts, of his diſturbing Miniſters, of magnifying himſelf, of his pretended Miracles, and other deluding Charms; on purpoſe to bewitch the people, like <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> his Predeceſſor. Wherefore in this conteſt there can be no Neuters: if God be God, ſerve him; if <hi>Baal,</hi> ſerve him; who can
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46060:8"/> have patience to ſee the Name of God thus openly Blaſphemed? he that can is no Chriſtian; he has not zeal for God, nor love to the ſouls of men: The Papiſts will not have the Pope called Antichriſt, nor ſpoken diſreſpectfully of; the <hi>Turk</hi> will not hear <hi>Mahomet</hi> blaſphemed; as we are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> let us ſtand for Chriſt, and the Chriſtian Religion. I have read how dangerous it is to foſter Hereticks, and ſhall <hi>England</hi> now become a nurſery of Quakeriſm, which ſpread itſelf like a Leproſie far and near, even to Nations beyond the Seas? And therefore ſince <hi>G. Whitehead, &amp;c.</hi> have printed the Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> which the poor ſilly ignorant Quakers run a whoring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as the Idolatrous <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did after the Golden Calf, I am zealouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to unmask the head of this <hi>Foxonian</hi> Tribe of Quakers, <hi>(i. e.) G. Fox;</hi> and in a remembrance of what I was once my ſelf, and that for many years, I can do no leſs: And in this ſhort Treatiſe I ſhall ſhew how <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> for the tree is known of the fruit.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECTION II.</head>
                  <p>SImon Magus <hi>lived in the Apoſtles time, as ſaith S.</hi> Luke, Acts <hi>8.9, 10.</hi> There was a certain man called Simon, which in fore time in the ſame City uſed Sorcery, and bewitched the people of Samaria; giving out that himſelf was ſome great one, to whom they all gave heed, from the leaſt to the greateſt, ſaying, this man is the great power of God. <hi>And ſaid</hi> Juſtin Martyr, Many adored him as the ſupream God, they gave heed to him, they believed and obeyed what he taught, they placed their hope and confidence in him. <hi>See</hi> Pool<hi>'s</hi> Synopſis <hi>of the Criticks, p. 1462. for more of this nature. And</hi> Eraſmus <hi>in his paraphraſe upon that place ſaith,</hi> A man there was among the <hi>Samaritans</hi> called <hi>Simon,</hi> a deceiver of the people, and a practiſer of deluſions; who before <hi>Philip</hi> came there, practiſed in that City Magick Art; and by his counterfeit Miracles had made the <hi>Samaritans</hi> fond of him; who by means of ſuch falſhood and deceit, avaunted himſelf before the ſimple and plain people, boaſting that he was an excellent Prophet, unto whom the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> from the higheſt to the loweſt, gave good heed; but nothing had he done in Jeſus name, and therefore they, as a people aſtoniſhed at ſuch monſtrous ſights, ſaid, This fellow is Gods own right hand, which is called Mighty. Many a day had he been with them, and long had he made them with his Sorcery to dote upon him, and therefore when he had once gotten him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a name with them of great eſtimation, many one believed him in all that he taught, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And beſides, as Hiſtory ſaith,</hi> Simon Magus <hi>was an early Blaſphemer of the Bleſſed Trinity, a ſlighter of the Scriptures, and a denyer of the Law of</hi> Moſes: <hi>from all which four things are obſervable,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. That</hi> Simon Magus <hi>gave out of himſelf that he was ſome great man, that he wrought counterfeit Miracles in his own Name, and never in the name of Jeſus of</hi> Nazareth.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. That all the</hi> Samaritans <hi>gave heed to him, from the leaſt to the greateſt, believing all he taught, ſaying, This man is the great power of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46060:8"/>
                     <hi>3. That he got himſelf a name of great eſtimation to be an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; they at laſt adored him as the Supreme God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. That he was a ſlighter of the Scripture, and a denyer of the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>a blaſphemer of the bleſſed Trinity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now how far</hi> G. Fox <hi>is of kin to</hi> Simon Magus <hi>will appear in the next Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the tree muſt be known by the fruit; men do not gather Grapes of Thorns, nor Figs of Thiſtles; this is a true meaſuring Line, being laid to Scripture Rule.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THat Geo. Fox <hi>gave out of himſelf that he was ſome great one.</hi> 2. <hi>That he wrought Counterfeit Miracles, and never in the name of Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For proof of the firſt of theſe read his Journal, <hi>p.</hi> 31. Being asked whether he was ſanctified, anſwered, <hi>Yes, for he was in the Paradice of God,</hi> ibid. <hi>The power of God thundered</hi> (ſaid <hi>George) amongſt them: And they</hi> (the worlds people) <hi>did fly like chaff before the wind,</hi> p. 60. <hi>So that it was a dreadful thing unto them when it was told them, the man in the Leathern Breeches is come.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 55. A woman ſaid that an Angel or Spirit came into <hi>Beverly</hi> Church, and ſpake the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things of God, to the aſtoniſhment of all that were there, and when it had done it paſſed away, and no man knew whence it came, nor whither it went, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This <hi>G. Fox</hi> owned himſelf to be the man, and left the relation under his own hand, which muſt be to magnifie himſelf. Again <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>Then did I ſee</hi> (ſaid <hi>Geo. Fox) the heavens opened:</hi> p. 45. <hi>Whileſt I was yet in the houſe of Correction</hi> (ſaid <hi>G. F.) there came unto me a Troop, ſaying, As I was ſitting in the Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-houſe</hi> (ſaid the Troop) <hi>hearing the Prieſt, the voice of the Lord came unto me ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, doſt thou not know that my ſervant</hi> (G. F.) <hi>is in priſon, go to him for direction; ſo I</hi> (ſaid <hi>G. F.) ſpake to his condition, and his underſtanding was opened.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 67. <hi>I call'd the Accuſer</hi> Judas, <hi>and ſaid</hi> Judas<hi>'s end ſhould be his, and that was the word of the Lord and of Chriſt thro me to him, and ſhortly after he hang'd himſelf.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Fra. Howgill <hi>of me, this man</hi> (G. F.) <hi>ſpeaks with authority, and not like the Scribes.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>Now I ſat on a Hay-ſtack, and ſpake nothing for ſome hours, the profeſſors being deſirous to hear me ſpeak, asked when I would begin, and when I would ſpeak? One preſent bid them wait, and told them, that the people waited upon Chriſt a long while before he ſpake.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 278. <hi>At</hi> Leith (<hi>in</hi> Ireland) <hi>the Inn-keeper told me, that the Council had granted forth Warrants to apprehend me; to whom I ſaid, What do you tell me</hi> (G. F.) <hi>of their Warrants againſt me, if there were a Cart-load of them I do not heed them.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 431. <hi>The takers and payers of Tythes muſt be teſtified againſt in the Lords power.</hi> Again, <hi>p.</hi> 438. <hi>Many friends were impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned at</hi> London <hi>and other places, for opening their Shop-wndows on Holydays and Faſt-days, which friends could not but do, for we were redeemed out of days by Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thus, Reader, I have given thee a ſmall ſample of <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s own words of himſelf in his Journal, ſhewing that himſelf was ſome great one: I am next coming to his Books, for another ſample, and when you have them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46060:9"/> them to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> touching that particular, and ſee which outſtrips and exceeds each other in magnifying themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The Tryal of <hi>G. Fox</hi> at <hi>Lancaſter</hi> Aſſize, p. 21. <hi>And before I came to the Bar I was moved to pray, and the thundering voice anſwered, I have glorified thee, and will glorifie thee again: And I was filled ſo full of Glory, that my head and ears were filled full of it: And when the Judges came up, they appeared all as dead men under me, &amp;c.</hi> Alluding to Chriſt, John 12.28. 16.14. and 17.1.</p>
                  <p>News coming up, <hi>&amp;c. Written from the mouth of the Lord, from one who is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſtands naked before the Lord, cloathed with Righteouſneſs, whoſe name is not known in the world, riſen up out of the North, which was propheſied of; but now it is fulfilled.</hi> G. Fox.</p>
                  <p>Several Petitions Anſwered, p. 60. <hi>My name is covered from the world, and the world knows not me, nor my name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> s Errand to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He that hath the ſame ſpirit that raiſed up Jeſus Chriſt from the dead, is equal with God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Battledoor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Introd. <hi>All Languages are to me no more than duſt, who was before Languages were, &amp;c.</hi> Alike to <hi>James Parnell,</hi> one of his Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>The Watcher, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 37. <hi>But to the end of all diſputes and arguments I am come, for before they was <hi>I am.</hi>
                     </hi> See <hi>W. P.</hi>'s <hi>Chriſt. Qua. and Dev. Teſt.</hi> p. 96. And you will find both <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Parnell</hi> call themſelves Chriſt, in <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s ſenſe: And that in <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s ſenſe he that ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was no more Chriſt than they, <hi>(i. e.) G. Fox</hi> and <hi>Ja. Parnell:</hi> for <hi>Fox</hi> ſaid he was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> in that he ſaid he was before Languages were: <hi>Parnell</hi> was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> in that he was before Arguments were; for between <hi>Abram</hi> and <hi>Lots</hi> Heardſmen there were Arguments. And for the Humanity of Chriſt, the Quakers deny it, as clearly as the <hi>Socinians</hi> deny his Godhead; read Sect. the xviii. thus I hope I have proved the firſt part of the Paragraph: And now to the ſecond, which is, that <hi>G. Fox</hi> works counterfeit maricles, and not in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt; for proof of this ſee his Journal, <hi>p.</hi> 170, 171, 30, 370, 373, 503. and there you will find <hi>G. F.</hi> ſpake to a woman, and the Lord (he ſays) raiſe her up: in 171 I find there is two miracles, and which to take I cannot tell, but one of theſe two it muſt be, <hi>viz.</hi> A Woman married a Man in Debt, and ſhe went diſtracted; ſent for <hi>G. Fox,</hi> he ſpake to her, ſhe mended. The other was two men fighting, whom <hi>G. F.</hi> being a ſtout man, parted; but neither in the Name of Jeſus. In p. 167. he tells us of many Miracles the Quakers wrought, but mentions not where, nor upon whom. Likewiſe <hi>Cley Pool</hi> had a fit of the Stone, and <hi>G. F.</hi> laid his hand on him, and afterwards he mended: One in <hi>Maryland,</hi> ſaid to be a Parliament Man (tho I am informed there is no Parliament there, and that ſpoils this Miracle) healed. In ſhort, they are all feigned, counterfeit Miracles, and none done (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> well obſerves of <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) in the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth.</hi> But to read the ſtory of <hi>Jo. Iſays</hi> broken Neck, 'twould make a melancholy man laugh: oh <hi>G. F.</hi> ſtand by him, and pity him and his Family. Well to work went <hi>G. F.</hi> and throws away his Gloves and Stick, ſaying, <hi>I</hi> got to him aſſoon as <hi>I</hi> could, <hi>I</hi> took hold of <hi>his</hi> hair, <hi>I</hi> took his head in both <hi>my</hi> hands, and ſet <hi>my</hi> knees againſt the tree; <hi>I</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:46060:9"/> raiſed his head: mark Reader here was all I, I, I, and my, my, not a word of Prayer, not a word like the Apoſtle, in the Name of Jeſus be thou healed; no: what can <hi>Whitehead</hi> ſay to this? is he not aſhamed of their horrible deluſions? I have ſaid enough to wiſe men: and bray a Fool in the Mortar, and they will not be wiſer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>AND the</hi> Foxonian <hi>Quakers gave héed unto</hi> G. Fox <hi>from the leaſt to the greateſt, believing all he taught, ſaying he is the power of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That they gave heed to him in all he taught, 'tis demonſtrable from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reaſons, but for brevity ſake I ſhall mention this, <hi>viz.</hi> of all the Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that ever <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſpake or wrote, never a Quaker of his Party ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned one paſſage, but either juſtified it, or if that could not be done, then excuſe it; ſee <hi>W. Pen</hi> in his Book <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> p. 44. Tho to do the diſſenting Quakers juſtice, who meet in <hi>Harp-lane,</hi> they did by their Book, <hi>An Anſwer to ſeveral paſſages, &amp;c.</hi> p. 10. condemn <hi>G. F.</hi>'s words in the <hi>Battledoor,</hi> as <hi>High Blaſphemy;</hi> and p. 6. ſaid <hi>Geo. Whitehead</hi> as guilty of the aforeſaid charge, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> of being a <hi>contentious Scribbler, of giving baſe names,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>in part of cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing groſs errors.</hi> Indeed when I ſaw this come forth, I was in hopes of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; but alas this was no ſooner come to my hand, but I had another ſent me which juſtifies <hi>G. Fox,</hi> and <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> in all their abomination, ſigned by
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Edw. Bruſh,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Waller Miers,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Cox,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Gilbert Laity,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Bathurſt,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Lower,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>William Phillips,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Mincks,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Vaughton,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Nath. Marks,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Cooper,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tim. Emmerton,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Feild,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Michael Ruſſel,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Knight,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hen. Goldney,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Bingly,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Charles Marſhall,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Will. Sanders,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Geo. Bowles,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Tomkins,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tho. Hutſon,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>John Evered,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dan. Wharly.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that when all theſe came out in the name of the reſt, I concluded the <hi>Foxonian</hi> Tribe, from the higheſt to the loweſt, believed all <hi>G. F.</hi> taught, how Blaſphemous ſoever it was. And now to the ſecond part of the paragraph, that they ſay <hi>he is the Power <hi>of God;</hi>
                     </hi> for proof of this ſee the third Table or Index to <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s Journal, under the Letter M, for Miracles, where 'tis thus ſaid, <hi>Miracles wrought by the Power of God.</hi> And when I turned to <hi>p.</hi> 370, 371, where one of the profoundeſt Miracles he did is recorded, and as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle too, there is nothing but I <hi>George Fox</hi> threw away my Stick and Gloves, I, I, I, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> ſay 'twas the life of Chriſt in him, I tell him No, it muſt be <hi>G. Fox,</hi> for the life of Chriſt in him need no Stick and Gloves: from whence 'tis plain they hold parallel with the poor deluded <hi>Samaritans,</hi> calling <hi>G. Fox</hi> the power of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46060:10"/>
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. THat G. Fox <hi>got a name of great eſtimation to be an excellent Prophet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til his Followers adored him as God.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fifth part Chriſt. Qua. diſting. p. 77.</hi> That <hi>G. Fox</hi> is bleſſed with honor ahove many Brethren, and that thouſands will ſtand by him in a heavenly record: That his <hi>Life Reigns</hi> and is <hi>Spotleſs,</hi> Innocent, and ſtill retains his Integrity; whoſe <hi>Eternal honour and Bleſſed renown</hi> remain ſtill: yea, his preſence and the dropping of his tender words in the Lords love was my ſouls Nouriſhment, &amp;c. <hi>for more of this ſee</hi> New Rome unm. <hi>from p. 42 to 48. Yea, (ſo dreadful was</hi> G. F.<hi>'s name to the people beyond Sea, that they publiſhed it to the world) viz.</hi> That mentioning the name <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> did prick them to the heart, <hi>&amp;c. See their book</hi> A true Account, &amp;c. <hi>p. 42.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Quakers Challenge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 6.</hi> Stand up <hi>Muggleton,</hi> who calls thy book a Looking-glaſs for <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> whoſe name thou art not worthy to take into thy mouth, who is a Prophet indeed, and hath been faithful in the Lords buſineſs from the beginning:<note place="margin">This <hi>Sel. Eccles</hi> who wrote the <hi>Quakers Challenge,</hi> is the Prophet, who prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, that <hi>John Story</hi> ſhould die within one year, being then very ill, who lived 4 years after; and as <hi>G. Fox</hi> ſaid, that neither himſelf nor his name was known, ſee Sect. 3d. Yea a Prophet equallized with Chriſt, a right <hi>Samaritan,</hi> &amp;c.</note> it was ſaid of Chriſt he was in the world and the world knew him not, <hi>ſo</hi> it may be ſaid of this true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, whom <hi>John</hi> ſaid he was not; but thou ſhalt feel this Prophet <hi>(i. e. G. F.)</hi> one day, as heavy as a Milſtone upon thee; and altho the world knows him not, yet he is known.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Next ſee an Abſtract of a Letter ſent to</hi> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>in his Life time, from</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes, <hi>by</hi> Joſiah Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l, <hi>one of their eminent Preachers, dated the 21ſt, 12th month, 1658. and every word of it vindicated by</hi> William Pen <hi>in their book ſtiled</hi> Judas and the Jews, &amp;c. <hi>p. 44. viz.</hi> Dear <hi>Geo. Fox,</hi> who art the Father of many Nations, whoſe life has reached thro us thy childen, even to the Iſles afar off; to the begetting many again to a lively hope for which Generations to come ſhall call <hi>thee Bleſſed,</hi> whoſe <hi>being</hi> and <hi>habitation</hi> is in the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>higheſt,</hi> in which <hi>thou Rules</hi> and <hi>Governs</hi> in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>thy Kingdom</hi> is <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> in <hi>Peace,</hi> and the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> thereof is <hi>without end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Next a Letter to</hi> G. Fox <hi>from</hi> John Audland <hi>out of the Weſt of</hi> England, <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what abſtracted,</hi> &amp;c. Dear and pretious one, in whom my life is bound up, my ſtrength in the ſtand; by thy breathings I am nouriſhed, by thee my ſtrength is renewed, life and ſtrength come from thee; holy one, daily do I find thy preſence with me, which doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly preſerve me, for I cannot raign but in thy preſence and power; pray for me, that I may ſtand in thy dread for evermore. I am thine, begotten and nouriſhed by thee, and in thy power am I preſerved, glory unto thee, holy one, for ever, <hi>&amp;c. See this Letter at large in</hi> The Diſcovery of the accurſed thing enlarged, <hi>&amp;c. p. See their book ſtiled, <hi>This is to go only amongſt Friends.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thou oh North of <hi>England,</hi> who art counted as deſolate and barren, and reckon'd the leaſt of the Nation,<note n="*" place="margin">Mich. 5.2. Matt. 2.6. Joh. 7 42.</note> yet out of thee did the branch ſpring<note n="†" place="margin">Zech. 3.8.</note>, and ſtar<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 24.17, 19.</note> ariſe, which gives light to all the Regions round about: In thee the Son of Righteouſneſs appeared<note n="†" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> with healing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46060:10"/> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and out of thee the terrors of the Lord proceeded, which makes the earth to tremble, and be removed; out of thee Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, did come forth: Lift up your voices, blow the Trumpet, ſound an Alarum out of the holy mountain, proclaim tbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable year, and the day of vengeance of our God; gird on your ſword on your loyns, put on the tried Armor;<note place="margin">Note this is one of their books the worlds people is not to ſee, it's to go only amongſt Friends.</note> ride on, ride on my brethren and fellow ſoldiers, make all plain before you; make the heathen tremble, and the uncircumciſed fall by the ſword; ſpare none neither Ox nor Aſs, neither old nor young; kill, cut off, deſtroy; bath your ſword in the blood of <hi>Amalek,</hi> and all the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> and <hi>Egyptians;</hi> hew <hi>Agag</hi> to pieces, break down the Rocks, cut down the Ceders, make the Devils (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Prieſts) ſubject, caſt out the unclean ſpirit, (<hi>i. e.</hi> that pay or receive Tyths) raiſe the dead, ſhut up in Priſon, bring out of Priſon, caſt in your Nets, launch into the deep; bind the tares in bundles, caſt them into the fire; the good Angel <hi>(i. e. G. Fox)</hi> is come, thruſt in your Cicles, reap the earth; ſilence all Diſputers and Diviners for ever; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph upon all the chaff, the mire and dung for ever; prepare your ſelves to battle, for the Nation doth defie our God, ſaying, <hi>Who is the God of the Quakers,</hi> A rebellious people that will not come under our Law, <hi>&amp;c. and ſo on, ſee</hi> New Rome unm. <hi>&amp;c. p. 85. more at large.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thus you ſee, that as 'tis written,</hi> Acts <hi>10.34.</hi> To him gave all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets witneſs, <hi>&amp;c. ſo you ſee that all the Quakers Prophets being 400 in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, give witneſs to</hi> Geo. Fox, <hi>and adore him, as the Branch, the Star, the Sun of Righteouſneſs, whoſe being and habitation is in the power of the higheſt, ruling in his Kingdom, the increaſe of which is without end, as ſay the Quakers his Idolatrous Adorers; by which 'tis clear he outſtrips</hi> Simon Magus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. THat G. Fox <hi>was a ſlighter of the Scriptures, a denyer of the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ordinances of Ieſus Chriſt, and a Blaſphemer of the Bleſſed Trinity.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 14.</hi> Your original is carnal, <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi> and the light is carnal, the Letter and your Baptiſm is carnal, and their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is carnal, and their Communion is carnal; ſo duſt is the Serpents meat, their original is but duſt which is the letter, which is death; ſo the Serpent feeds upon duſt, and their Goſpel is duſt, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> which is the letter, <hi>p. 34.</hi> A voice and a word to all you Deceivers, who deceive the people, and Blaſphemers who utter forth your Blaſphemy and Hypocriſy; that tell people of a Sacrament, and tell them it is the Ordinance of God; bluſh, bluſh, and tremble before the Almighty, for dreadful is he that will pour out his vengeance upon you, who live in the Witchery and bewitch the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and theſe things (<hi>i. e.</hi> Baptiſm and the Lords Supper) that God never commanded, are given forth by you who are brazened with deceit: and no Witch muſt live in <hi>Iſrael, (i. e.</hi> no Prieſt).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Quakers Refuge fixed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 17.</hi> Whether the firſt Penman of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures was <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Hermes,</hi> or whether both theſe are not one; or whether there are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46060:11"/> not many words contained in the Scriptures which were not ſpoken by the Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit; whether ſome words were not ſpoken by the Grand Impoſtor; ſome by wicked men, ſome by wiſe men ill applied, ſome by good men ill expreſſed; ſome by falſe Prophets and yet true; ſome by true Prophets and yet falſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now this being propoſed as doubtful, overthrows the certainty and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures; for if what the true Prophets ſpake was falſe, and what wiſe and good men ſpoke was either ill applied or ill expreſſed, and what the falſe Prophets ſpoke be true, what certainty is here: this put to the Quakers practice in laying aſide in their Families, as well as in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the uſe of the Ten Commandments, Lords Prayer, and the Apoſtles Creed, together with what is above recited, is plain, that</hi> Geo. Fox <hi>and his Followers are Slighters of the Scriptures. Now to the 3d part of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph,</hi> viz. <hi>A Blaſphemer of the Bleſſed Trinity, one of his Sons books, The Sandy Foundation ſhaken,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 10.</hi> No one ſubſtance can have three diſtinct ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencies, and preſerve its own unity; for granting them <hi>(i. e. Trinitarians)</hi> the moſt favourable definition, every ſubſiſtence will have its own ſubſtance, ſo that three diſtinct ſubſiſtences will require three diſtinct ſubſtances or beings, conſequently three Gods, <hi>p. 16.</hi> The vulgar doctrine of ſatisfaction being dependent on the ſecond perſon of the imagined Trinity refuted from Scripture, <hi>&amp;c. ſays</hi> W. Pen; <hi>but I ſay neither he, nor all the Sons of</hi> Simon Magus, <hi>are able to refute that Article of the true Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VII.</head>
                  <p>I Am now coming to <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> the firſt Founder of the Jeſuits, and to ſhew that as <hi>G. Fox</hi> was one with <hi>Simon Magus</hi> in Doctrine, yet in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline he very much reſembles <hi>Ignatius Loyola;</hi> and before I proceed, I ſhall ſhew, that I am not alone in this opinion, and that from the judgment of two Learned Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> out of two books, the one intituled, <hi>The Good Old Way, &amp;c.</hi> p. 121, 122. <hi>But of all the Sects which are among us, undoubtedly the Quakers have been, and are, moſt eminently ſerviceable to our common Adverſary; for their principles are ſuch as could not come out of any other Mint but the Jeſuits. And truly no opinions can more reſemble theirs, than thoſe that are held by that crafty and perverſe Sect: do they (the Quakers) not think themſelves as infallible, as the Romaniſts think the Pope himſelf to be: and do they not ſay, that one reaſon why they divide from us is, becauſe we confeſs our ſelves to be men ſubject unto error: do they not lower the Magiſtrates Authority (as the Jeſuits do) and by all imaginable methods endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to render him contemptible; do they not villify the holy Scriptures (as the Jeſuits do) and call the Bible a dead Letter; do they not cry up the light, the light; juſt as the Jeſuits cry up tradition, tradition: do they not think themſelves to be the only people of God, (as the Jeſuits think their Faction to be) and count all others who are not of their Communion Reprobates and damned perſons; do they not take it for granted, that they are perfect and cannot ſin? Why, do but turn the Tables, and behold it is Jeſuitiſm upon which they build the Doctrine of Meritorious good Works; for where there is not perfection there can be no Merit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46060:11"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the moſt lucky and advantageous principle that ever was infus'd into them, is this; that they muſt not by any means ſwear, tho call d unto it by due Authority: The Jeſuit was no Fool when he taught them this, for hereby he keeps out of harms way, and ſhelters h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mſelf from a neceſſity of taking any Oaths of Supremacy or Allegiance; this Principle therefore they do arrantly guard, and make many propoſals that they may be allowed this, and as long as 'tis allowed it will be impoſſible to hunt our Enemies out of the Heard, or to diſtinguiſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed between a Quaker and a Jeſuit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By this any unprejudiced Man may ſee, that this ſullen and dogged Sect is the Jeſuits natural and undoubted Iſſue, tho like other baſtards they are aſhamed to own their father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> p. 282. <hi>Yet any one who compares them</hi> (i. e. <hi>Jeſuits and Quakers) would imagin the Life of</hi> Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius <hi>had been their great Exampler: I know not whether any of that innocent and religious Order of Jeſuits had any hand in forming this new Society</hi> (i. e. <hi>Quakers) among us, as has been frequently ſuggeſted; but if one may gueſs the Father by the Childs likeneſs,</hi> Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Loyola <hi>the Founder of the Jeſuits, was at leaſt the Grandfather of the Quakers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And now it remains, that <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> and <hi>G. Fox</hi> compare notes, that we may rightly underſtand, whether indeed the Quakers be the natural Iſſue of the Jeſuits, as both theſe learned Divines agree they are, and if they be, let us lay this ſpurious off-ſpring at <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> s door; but let us judge the tree by the fruit. 1. Did <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> cry down the Scriptures; ſo do the Quakers, witneſs the contemptible names they beſtow upon them, as <hi>beaſtly ware, carnal letter, duſt, death,</hi> and <hi>ſerpents meat.</hi> 2. Did <hi>Ignatius,</hi> whoſe Life was exemplary, delight in and read the Papiſts Legend of the Lives, Miracles, and Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſms of their Saints, as Don <hi>Quixot,</hi> rather than the Scriptures; ſo do the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, who read their own Epiſtles in their meetings for worſhip, and ſuffer none to call the ſame <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Canons.</hi> 3. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> preach in the Streets, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-places, on Bulks and Hayſtacks, in oppoſition to Authority, ſo did the Quakers for many years. 4. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> exalt his own ſufferings, ſo do the Quakers, ſaying <hi>their ſufferings are greater and more unjuſt than the ſufferings of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and Martyrs,</hi> read <hi>Burroughs</hi> works, p. 273. 5. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to put off his Hat to men in authority; the Quakers do the ſame. 6. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> allegoriſe the Scripture, the death and ſufferings of Chriſt, his paſſion, attonement, reſurrection and aſcention to be within, ſo do the Quakers. 7. Was <hi>Ignatius</hi> a Tradeſman; <hi>G. Fox</hi> was a poor Journeyman Shoemaker, and wrought Journey-work for <hi>George Gee</hi> of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and ſo are many of his Followers, the Preachers amongſt the Quakers; and <hi>G. Fox</hi> was no Scholar, but ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of being thought ſo; for inſtance, his Book ſtiled <hi>A Battledoor for Teachers and Profeſſors,</hi> Anno 1660. to learn ſingular and plural, <hi>viz. tu</hi> and <hi>vos,</hi> with the form and figure of a Battledoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, to imitate a Childs penny Horn-book, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining divers learned Languages, as <hi>Greek, Hebrew, Latin, Syriack, Italian, Caldee,</hi> and divers others; and all this noiſe to bring into contempt both the Gentry of this famous, chriſtian, and learned Country, and the learned Clergy. 8. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> and his Diſciples pretend to a gift of diſcerning, to know the thoughts of their Neighbours, <hi>ſo</hi> did <hi>G. Fox,</hi> who ſaid <hi>the Quakers have a ſpirit given them beyond their fore-fathers, and know who are Saints, who are Devils, and who are Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46060:12"/> without ſpeaking ever a word,</hi> &amp;c. ſaying, <hi>as Chriſt is ſo are we</hi> (Quakers) <hi>in this world,</hi> Gr. myſt. p. 89. 10. Did <hi>Ignatius</hi> travel up and down preaching; working Miracles, ſeeing Viſions, to <hi>Montſorret, Manreſa, Barcelona, Padua;</hi> and after he was ſoundly beaten for not putting off his Hat to the Governor of <hi>Barcelona,</hi> back again to <hi>Salamanca,</hi> where he was put into the Dungeon, and there chain'd to a Poſt, at which he gloried as much as ever his Grand Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren did; after that to <hi>Antwerp, Paris, Roven,</hi> where he ſtood up to the neck in dirt to repreſent to his Companions the filthineſs of ſin, and to get commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the people, and thereby ſome followers; as <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his followers uſed to go into Churches, till ſome or other brake their Shins, or made their Noſe bleed, and then ſome ſilly tender people would follow them, into ſome poor womans houſe, where they would hold forth, and tell them do you ſee the fruits of the Prieſts; and ſo gat here and there a few unwary Diſciples, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at laſt <hi>Ignatius</hi> got to <hi>Rome</hi> to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> 3d, and got his Bull to confirm the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Jeſus, <hi>October</hi> 3. 1540. and for more of <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi>'s Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I refer the Reader to the Works of <hi>Maffejus Orlandinus</hi> and <hi>Ribadeneira,</hi> who wrote his Life.</p>
                  <p>So did <hi>G. Fox</hi> to ſettle Quakeriſm travel up and down, diſturbing Miniſters in Churches, preaching in Barns, Market-places, on Hayſtacks, on Bulks, working Miracles, yea as true ones as <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> and as like them as if they were Twins, quite through <hi>England, Wales, Ireland, Holland, Barbadoes, Virginia, Maryland,</hi> and many places more, as his Journals ſet forth; ſo that 'tis needleſs further to blot paper to manifeſt the parity between <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>George</hi> his Grandſon: if <hi>Ignatius</hi> pretended to a ſinleſs perfection, <hi>George</hi> and his followers are full as good at it, read his <hi>Gr. myſt.</hi> p. 33, 107, 267. where he tells you he can give an infallible character of another mans ſtate and condition; and that he who is not infallible in his judgment, council and advice, is no Miniſter of Chriſt, that the Quakers are the only Miniſters of Chriſt. And as a further proof that <hi>G. Fox</hi> and his followers are <hi>Ignatius</hi> his dear Children, read the Works following, and a hundred more of their Books, and you ſhall not find one paſſage wherein they make confeſſion of their ſins to God, and beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for Chriſts ſake, according to the example of the Prophets, Apoſtles, Saints and Martyrs, in all ages; neither if you go to 1000 Meetings ſhall you hear one of their Preachers have ſuch an expreſſion in their mouths, <hi>viz.</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their ſins, and begging pardon for Jeſus Chriſts ſake: And for example I have read great part of theſe Books following, and cannot find ſuch a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: I was alſo a Quaker 25. years, and in all that time I do not remember ſuch a paſſage: If any think I wrong the Quakers, let them read and ſearch as I have done, and ſhew me ſuch a paſſage if they can: <hi>The Books by me moſt examined are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Edw. Burroughs,</hi> in folio, containing pages</cell>
                           <cell>896</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sam. Fiſhers</hi> Works, in folio, pages</cell>
                           <cell>954</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <note place="margin">Read <hi>Qua. detected,</hi> p. 8. to 12. and <hi>New R. unmaskt,</hi> p. 18.</note>
                              <hi>Fr. Howgillt</hi> Works, in folio</cell>
                           <cell>709</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> his Journal, in folio</cell>
                           <cell>632</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Geo. Fox</hi> his Great Myſt. in folio</cell>
                           <cell>407</cell>
                        </row>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46060:12"/>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Will. Smiths</hi> Works, in folio</cell>
                           <cell>565</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>W. Pens</hi> and <hi>Geo. Whiteheads</hi> Chriſt. Qua. in folio</cell>
                           <cell>555</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>W. Baylys</hi> Works, in quarto</cell>
                           <cell>774</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Rich. Hubberthorps</hi> Works, in quarto</cell>
                           <cell>374</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>W. Pens</hi> Invalidity, in quarto</cell>
                           <cell>451</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>6317</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus I have given you a ſample of their Books, and read as many of them as you pleaſe, and if thou art a Quaker, and has but a ſpark of Chriſtianity left in thee, I admoniſh thee, and that for thy own Souls ſake, read theſe Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.4. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8, 9. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51.1, 2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.6. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.41, 42. <hi>Job</hi> 7.20. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.4, 5, 20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10, 11. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.47. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. And then compare the practice of the Saints of old to the practice of the Quakers, and they do no more reſemble each other than black does white. Here you will ſee that <hi>Moſes</hi> that meek and good man, <hi>David</hi> a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods own heart, <hi>Iſaiah, Jeremiah, John, Job,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nay, ſo far are they from this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that one of their Preachers, In the Book, <hi>A Muſick Lect.</hi> &amp;c. ſays, p. 22, <hi>I do affirm that if</hi> John (the Apoſtle) <hi>had ſaid he had been a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he had Lyed,</hi> &amp;c. Oh Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> 
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> the beloved of the Lord, <hi>Paul</hi> the great Apoſtle; they all acknowledge themſelves ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, they begg'd pardon for Chriſts ſake: But you can never hear that <hi>G. Fox, Sam. Fiſher, Ed. Burrows, W. Pen, G. Whitehead, W. Smith, Fra. Hawgil, Wm. Bayly,</hi> nor <hi>Richard Hubberthorn,</hi> in all theſe 6317 pages that they make the leaſt confeſſion of ſin, and that they ever beg pardon for the ſame. And this I take, and have done for many years, to be an Argument that they are of a different faith and practice to the Apoſtles, the Prophets, the Martyrs, and all true Chriſtians to this day. And if any be deſirous to be further ſatisfied read my book, <hi>The Quakers detected,</hi> &amp;c. p. 8 to 12. <hi>New Rome unmasked,</hi> &amp;c. p. 16 to 20, where I have largely treated on this head; I alſo recommend an ingenious piece called <hi>The Quakers Quibbles,</hi> which to this day they have not been able to anſwer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
                  <p>THe Invalidity of <hi>John Faldo</hi>'s Vindication, <hi>&amp;c. part 1. page 103. cap. 5. I find</hi> William Pen <hi>making a piteous moan againſt</hi> John Faldo: <hi>And begging (like a poor Fryer) of his Reader,</hi> to do a poor people right for once, <hi>viz.</hi> Reader, I beſeech thee for truths ſake, on whoſe ſide ſoever thou ſhalt find it to be, to examine with all impartiality his Charge, our Anſwer, his Reply, and our Rejoynder; if his Honeſty, Reaſon and Juſtice hold any proportion to his great Confidence, we yield: But if upon an impartial conſideration he ſhall be found to clip and pervert our matter, and to ſhuffle with us in his own, <hi>once do a poor people Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>William <hi>I have read both ſides, and do ſay that he hath contracted yours fairly, and taken in the ſenſe fully, and what you add to it is but your gloſs:</hi> Edward Burroughs <hi>Doctrine is plain and poſitive, which teach,</hi> That is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46060:13"/> from God to me, what he commands to another; neither did any of the Saints which we read of, in Scripture, act by the Command which was to another, not having the command to themſelves: I challenge to find an example for it, they obeyed every one the command to themſelves, <hi>&amp;c. See</hi> his works, <hi>p. 47. And Mr.</hi> Faldo <hi>repeats ſo much of your Anſwer, as carries the ſtrength of your Argument, which is this, viz.</hi> No Command in Scripture is any further obliging upon any man, than as he finds a conviction upon his Conſcience; otherwiſe men ſhould be engaged without, if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt Conviction; a thing unreaſonable in men. <hi>Thus far</hi> Pen.</p>
                  <div type="observation">
                     <head>Obſervation.</head>
                     <p>The Obſervation I make is this, that your Friend <hi>Burroughs</hi> Doctrine is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Ranteriſm, and that by the Doctrine of <hi>William Pen</hi> too, <hi>A brief examination of Lib. Spiritual,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>per W. P.</hi> p. 3. <hi>For it is a dangerous principle, and pernicious to the true Religion, and which is worſe, 'tis the root of Ranteriſm to aſſert that nothing is a duty incumbent upon thee, but what thou art perſwaded (or convinced) is thy duty.</hi> Again p. 11. <hi>The enemy is at work to ſcatter the minds of friends by that <hi>Looſe Plea,</hi> what haſt thou to do with me, leave me to my freedom, and to the Grace of God in my ſelf; this is a deviation from, and a pervertion of the antient principle of truth; if any one ſhall ſay I ſee no evil in paying Tythes, I ſee no evil in marrying by a Prieſt, I ſee no evil in keeping my Shop ſhut upon the worlds holy days, and Chriſtmas days (and faſt days) which is confuſion it ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay my Obſervation is this: the Quakers will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as an indiſpenſable duty an abſolute conformity to their orders, to their laws, to their canons and decrees; and if any plead to ſtay till they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the reaſonableneſs of their commands, this is Ranteriſm, yea down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Ranteriſm, altho it be to pay Tythes which the Law commands, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch days commanded by Authority, and which, as ſuch, the Scriptures enjoyn, which ſay, <hi>be ſubject to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> &amp;c. But to obey the Scripture commands, as ſuch, that's no obligation (by <hi>Wm. Pens</hi> doctrine) unleſs a man be convinced thereof, or unleſs he have the command anew, and as immediately as the inſpired Apoſtles and Prophets had; ſee my Book <hi>de Chriſtiana Libertate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 30 to 45. where the Quakers impoſition about things of indifferency are at large handled.</p>
                     <p>But Mr. <hi>Faldo</hi> tells the Quakers (and I think not without good reaſon) that this Doctrine of the Quakers ſprings from ſuch a pernitious principle as carry all iniquity in the womb of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But as <hi>W. Pen</hi> deſires, beſeeches and begs, that I ſhould for once do a poor [deluded] people right, ſo I will anſwer his requeſt, and the way to do it is, to ſet down <hi>Burroughs</hi> Doctrine, and <hi>W. Pens</hi> Anſwer, at leaſt ſo much of it, as carry the ſtrength of his argument, <hi>viz. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows</hi> Works, <hi>p.</hi> 47. <hi>That is no command from God to me, what he commands to another; di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> any of the Saints which we read of in ſcripture, act by the command which was to another, not having the command to themſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whereas from the recited Doctrine of <hi>Burroughs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Faldo</hi> charges the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers to teach, that no commands in Scripture, as ſuch, are binding to us; which he accounted as ſuch a pernicious principle, as carried all iniquity in the womb
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46060:13"/> of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſalve which, pray hear Mr. <hi>Pens</hi> anſwer, <hi>To this, ſaith he, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer briefly and plainly; no commands in ſcripture are any further obliging upon any man, than as he finds a conviction upon his conſcience; otherwiſe men ſhould be ingaged without, if not againſt conviction; a thing unreaſonable in a man.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now I cannot ſee how <hi>W. Pens</hi> argument can anſwer the end propoſed, ſince 'tis very hard for the Quakers, nay impoſſible, to be convinced of the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of their obedience to Scripture commands, as ſuch, if they adhere to the Quakers Doctrine, and names of contempt they frequently caſt upon it, Firſt for names, <hi>viz. Beaſtly ware, carnal letter, the husk, duſt, death, ſerpents meat; ſome of it ſpoke by the grand Impoſtor, ſome by wicked Men, ſome by true Prophets yet falſe, ſome by wiſe and good Men, yet either ill applied or ill expreſſed:</hi> And that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Moſes or Hermes was the firſt Penman remains a queſtion,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay here is no ground to hope, that theſe Teachers will ever convince their Hearers of their duty of obedience to Scripture commands, as ſuch: Again, that the people <hi>may as well burn the Scriptures as their Books.</hi> Again, <hi>If ever you own Chriſts and the Apoſtles, you will ever own our Writings,</hi> (ſay the Quakers) <hi>which are given forth by the power and ſpirit of God.</hi> Again, <hi>What is ſpoken from the ſpirit of him in any, is of as great authority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and greater;</hi> and very much to this effect, as in this Treatiſe, as alſo in <hi>New Rome Arraigned,</hi> is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved from the Books of their Teachers of greateſt note: Inſomuch that there ſeems no poſſibility for the conviction of their followers (who adhere and believe ſuch doctrine) of their duty of obedience to Scripture commands, as alſo may appear from their practice, as for example Chriſt ſaid, go <hi>teach all nations, bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>do this in remembrance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> me,</hi> &amp;c. here is two poſitive commands which the Quakers have quite thrown off, upon their principle, that no commands of God which he commanded to others are binding; now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they have a command from God, as the Apoſtles had, at leaſt until (as <hi>Pen</hi> ſaith) they are convinced 'tis their duty to obey; which is impoſſible, if they tell them, <hi>'tis Conjuration to preach out of the Scriptures, that they are beaſtly ware, ſerpents meat, duſt, and deaths,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Again hear what one of their moſt noted Teachers ſays, <hi>A Muſick Lecture,</hi> &amp;c. p. 35. <hi>Where they</hi> (the worlds people) <hi>are, I was, in performances, in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, in hearing, in reading, in prayers, and faſting; but when I came to bend my mind to that of God in me,</hi> (viz. <hi>Quakeriſm) I durſt not give God thanks for the Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als ſet before me,</hi> &amp;c. And the reaſon is plain; he not having the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Apoſtles had; for if Scripture precept had been binding, he had not only the command, but example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and the like may be urged for their diſobedience to the Laws of the Land, particularly about Tythes, which <hi>W. Pen</hi> and the Quakers make criminal in their hearers to pay, as likewiſe to ſhut up their Shop-windows on Faſt days commanded by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, theſe are made capital ſins in the hearers. But for non-ſubmiſſion to their own humane inventions, they charge them with Ranteriſm; thus have they (like their Predeceſſors the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who ſtrained at a Gnat and ſwallowed a Camel) made void the commandments of God, and precepts of the Goſpel of none effect by their tradition. Thus 'tis apparent that this Doctrine, <hi>That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46060:14"/> no commands of God in Scripture are any further obliging upon any man than he finds a conviction upon his conſcience,</hi> is ſo pernitious, <hi>that it carries all iniquity in the womb of it:</hi> And that this poſition opens the Flood-gates to all error, atheiſm, impiety and wickedneſs; for if conviction be all the ground of obedience to the commands of Scripture, and that no man until he is convinced that he is obliged to obey the commands of God laid down in the Scripture; then all rational Laws, Orders and Governments, both divine and humane, are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned; and from the date of this poſition a ſtop is put, ſo far as 'tis received and imbraced, to all Religion and Piety towards God: and upon this bottom, as their principal foundation and corner ſtone, the Quakers firſt roſe in the North, breaking all Law, Order and Government, diſturbing the Miniſters in their Churches, and all other Societies; for they were not convinced that they ought to obey Magiſtrates, nor their Laws; and how far they ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this principle this Treatiſe will ſhew: (tho I grant for ſelf-ends they are ſomewhat reformed, and to maintain their Grandeur, their Trade, and to get into the favour of the Government, that in time they may come to be Juſtices of Peace) For it is certain that this poſition, together with their other doctrine, take away and rob the Scriptures of their divine Authority, leaving all looſe and uncertain; and where this doctrine will end, were it generally embraced, God only knows: for the Quakers conſcience being hardened by the Doctrine of their Teachers, againſt the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Laws of the Land; the Papiſts, the Jeſuits, the Turks, the Arians, the Socinians, the Antitrinitarians, all may as well plead to be left, whether to obey Scripture commands as the Quakers; and the Hearers of them all, in all probability, as like to be convinced by their Teachers, as the Quakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who yet at the ſame time injoyn their Hearers not to pay Tythes, not to marry unleſs they publiſh their intention before their Womans Meeting, not to marry by a Prieſt, not to ſhut up their Shop on a Faſt day, but to keep it open in Teſtimony againſt the command of the Magiſtrate and his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and a hundred things more; and for non-ſubmiſſion to theſe injunctions there muſt be no plea, nor liberty given, nor forbearance, until conviction; but the Scripture commands are not, ſay they, obliging, unleſs a man be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IX.</head>
                  <p>HAving by the foregoing ſhewed <hi>W. Pen</hi> to be for and againſt himſelf, for conformity to the laws, orders and decrees of <hi>G. Fox;</hi> conviction, or no conviction, againſt conformity to the commands of God in Scripture, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs convinced, ſhewing himſelf thereby to be <hi>tot quot &amp; omnis,</hi> every thing and nothing; I am now coming to the latter part of the paragraph, wherein you ſorely complain of Mr. <hi>Faldo; But if upon an impartial conſideration he ſhall be found to clip or pervert our matter, and to ſhuffle with us in his own, <hi>Once do a poor people right,</hi>
                     </hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46060:14"/>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Pen,</hi> I am loath to provoke you, but if I ſhould I do not fear you; you complain of Mr. <hi>Faldo</hi>'s clipping and perverting your matter, and ſhuffling with you in his word: a crime no people upon the face of the whole earth more guilty than your ſelves, and at which none better than your ſelf, <hi>G. Whitebread,</hi> and <hi>G. Fox</hi> in his time; and I muſt tell you <hi>G. W.</hi> hath ſtood in great need of you, and does ſtill, one that can make a black thing appear white; but I fear the Quakers will not yet depute you, and my reaſon is, Mr. <hi>Meads</hi> averſneſs to your Preface to <hi>Fox</hi> his Journal being bound up therewith, but like ſome Lackey, it is forced to run ſhrugging afoot in a poor thin blue coat, waiting at the Readers Elbow like <hi>A Noun Adjective,</hi> wanting a word to ſhew its ſignification, as well as why it's left to ſhift for it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Well, <hi>William,</hi> I have not forgot your complaint, I am now coming to do right between you. As to Mr. <hi>Faldo,</hi> I have not read all he writ, but ſo far as I have, I find him fair and ingenuous, leaving out your gloſſes, wiping off your paintings, and diſcovering your fallacies; but <hi>William,</hi> caſt an eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>G. Fox</hi> s <hi>Gr. myſt.</hi> and compare it with the Books which he pretends to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and you will find it the greateſt Myſtery of Iniquity that ever appeared in the world, under pretence of a religious conteſt, of which Mr. <hi>Criſp</hi> has made a clear diſcovery, in his Book entitled, <hi>The Diſcovery of the accurſed thing in the</hi> Foxonian <hi>Quakers Camp enlarged,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>An Eſſay,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to allay</hi> G. F. <hi>s Spirit.</hi> Oh the horrible, clipping, mincing, and ſhameful pervertions, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſentences in two, taking the middle of a line, and leaving both ends, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the ſenſe, laming the argument, and defacing the whole matter; and if you pleaſe to do me right for once, againſt his Son and your Companion, that ſtood up ſtoutly for you when time was, <hi>(i. e.) G. W.</hi>'s anſwer ſtiled, <hi>The content Apoſt. recharged,</hi> &amp;c. to mine entitled <hi>Battering Rams againſt New Rome,</hi> &amp;c. where he took one line here, another there, and ſometimes five words out of the middle of a line, ſometimes but one word in a line, and leaves the next, and take the next, and leap two or three lines off, and take two or three words more, ſee <hi>New Rome unmaskt,</hi> p. 75. where this is fully diſcovered; it may be ſome may think this is not worth the mentioning, but if they do but conſider firſt, how they have prevailed with theſe people to believe, that what their Teachers ſay is by an infallible ſpirit, they will not err a jot, but do right to all impartially; next that they hinder their Hearers from reading the Anſwers, or ſelling Books that are againſt them, together with their way of ſpreading their own Books, which ſuggeſt this; and I do ſay, it is one of the cunningeſt ſtratagems that Satan has aſſiſted them in, and a deep deſign to miſrepreſent their Adverſaries: I could write a Folio on this head, but <hi>Fox</hi> his Book ſtiled, <hi>The Great myſt.</hi> being examined and compared is a ſufficient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, and if they will not examine, but the blind will follow their blind Leaders, be it upon themſelves; for what can a man ſay to ſuch as are willingly ignorant, and reſolve to oppoſe conviction.</p>
                  <p>I remember one little pretty ſtory in <hi>Fox</hi>'s Journal, ſee the 3d Table or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex <hi>Treachery againſt</hi> Geo. Fox <hi>his Horſe:</hi> Alas <hi>treaſon;</hi> for <hi>W. Pen</hi> knows <hi>G. F</hi> was a King, if he that has a Kingdom be a King, ſee <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> p. 44,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46060:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 45, 46. of his own juſtifying too. Well, however it was either Treachery or Treaſon, that's certain, as you may find it printed in the 255 page, <hi>And I looked back, and</hi> (the Hoſtler) <hi>was filing his Pocket with the Provender that was giving to my Horſe,</hi> &amp;c. I confeſs it was a naughty trick, and the worſe conſidering whoſe Horſe it was; but whether it deſerves to be chronicled I leave the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge. But Friend <hi>William,</hi> if you pleaſe to look into the 77 page of <hi>G. F.</hi> his <hi>Great myſtery,</hi> there you will find him juſtifying Felony, upon pretence of a motion, which ſhew that the 8th Commandment, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.15. was not binding to the Quakers, at leaſt to <hi>G. Fox</hi> their great Apoſtle and Prophet, and <hi>Jacob</hi> of the age: well pray hear him, <hi>And as for any being moved of the Lord to take away your</hi> (the Miniſters) <hi>hour-glaſs from you, by the eternal power it is owned,</hi> &amp;c. Here you ſee he owns Theft in the Quakers, with this proviſo, That <hi>if they be moved to it:</hi> And what Thief will not (to ſave his Bacon, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is) ſay he is moved: But the poor Thieviſh Hoſtler did but ſteal 2 or 3 handfuls of Oats and he muſt be upon Record to poſterity for a Thief; only <hi>G. F.</hi> was ſo kind as not to write his name down, no more than he did the names of ſeveral upon whom he wrought his Miracles, nor indeed where they dwelt; only ſome in <hi>Maryland,</hi> ſome in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and ſome in <hi>Ireland.</hi> But as to <hi>G. F.</hi> owning the Felony 'tis not ſtrange, for if he was not convinced at that time of his duty to Gods command in the 8th Commandment, he is by <hi>W. Pen</hi> juſtified; and that this poſition is of a dangerous tendency, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed carry in it all iniquity, I ſhall yet further obſerve.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. X.</head>
                  <p>HAving already treated of the Quakers Doctrine, particularly that poſition which ſays, <hi>That no command in Scripture is any further obliging upon any man, than as he finds a conviction upon his own conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. which is ſuch a pernicious principle, as Mr. <hi>Faldo</hi> ſaid, that it carries all iniquity in the womb of it, and indeed is the very floodgate by which Quakeriſm was firſt let in among us, which came in as a mighty ſtream, flowing over all our Banks of Laws, Order and Government, both divine and humane, overturning the very Ordinances in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; the authority of the Scriptures, to the great ſcandal of our Chriſtian Religion; and in the mean while valuing their own Papers, Laws, and Orders, as ſuperior to them; And therefore, as I have begun with the firſt planting of Quakeriſm, which was in the year 1650. and ſhewed by what arts they have come on, and advanced their Errors, I am now coming to ſhew the way of <hi>Lucius</hi> the firſt Chriſtian King (as Hiſtory ſaith) that the world ever knew, to propagate the Chriſtian Faith: he did not ſtay at this place and that to write Papers and Books to ſpread truth; nor did the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> at that time order him ſo to do; as was the practice of <hi>Geo. Fox:</hi> no, <hi>to the Law,</hi> and to the <hi>Teſtimony, <hi>this</hi>
                     </hi> was the way that every planter of the true Chriſtian Faith took, of which I will give you a noble inſtance:<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Eng.</hi> Chron. by <hi>John Heath,</hi> p. 19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>This Royal
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46060:15"/> King</hi> Lucius <hi>being mindful of Religion (that deareſt part of Government) more than any other conſideration, the better to proſper the work ſo proſperouſly begun, ſent two learned men to</hi> Elutherus <hi>then Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>to be farther inſtructed in the Chriſtian Faith, who thereupon ſent him</hi> Fagarius <hi>and</hi> Damianus, <hi>with his Letter in the following words (as ſaith the Hiſtorian</hi>) viz. <hi>You have received in the Kingdom of</hi> Briton, <hi>by Gods mercy, both the Law and Faith of Chriſt; you have both the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, out of the ſame (thro Gods Grace) by the Advice of your Realm, take a Law, and by the ſame, through Gods Sufference, rule your Kingdom of</hi> Brittain, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Having ſuch a good example from this Learned Biſhop, and Religious King; I ſhall firſt ſet down ſome Scriptures which have been both by Kings and Subjects thought ſpecial commands, and binding and obliging all men, whether all have been ſo perſwaded yea or nay; yet I ſay the faithful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in all ages and generations have taken them as their Rule of Obedience, and to be of that authority to quell and ſubdue all thoſe diabolical deluſions which will ſuggeſt the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> Mat. 22.21. <hi>Render therefore unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and unto God the things that are Gods.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to principalities and powers, to obey magiſtrates, to be ready to every good work.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13, 14, 17. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as ſupream; or unto governors, as unto them that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well. Honour all men, love the brotherhood, fear God, honour the King.</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2, 3. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of God; whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation; for rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil.</hi> Wilt thou<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>G. F.</hi> heed not a Cart Load of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</note> then not be afraid of the power; do that which is good and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>W. Tyndals</hi> works, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the obedience of a Chriſtian man, <hi>p.</hi> 111.</note>For God hath made the King in every Realm judge over all, and over him there is no Judge; he that reſiſteth the King reſiſteth God: If the Subjects ſin they muſt be brought to the Kings judgment: if the King ſin, he muſt be reſerved unto the judgment of God; and as it is to reſiſt the King, ſo is it to reſiſt his Officers which are ſet, or ſent to execute the Kings commandment; for it is written, let every ſoul ſubmit himſelf unto the authority of the higher powers:<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>G. W.</hi> what think you of this Doctrine.</note> here is no man exempt; but all <hi>ſouls</hi> muſt obey.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have given a brief account of the Chriſtian Faith. Firſt what Chriſt, who is the Head of the Chriſtian Church, and Author of the Chriſtian Faith, he ſaid, <hi>Render unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars;</hi> and his Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> bid <hi>Titus, put the believing Chriſtians in mind to obey Magiſtrates:</hi> and to confirm this point <hi>St. Peter</hi> is very expreſs, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake;</hi> not ſo much that he favours us, or is kind, and governs gently, by wholſome Laws, theſe things indeed are good, and great mercies to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but our ſubmiſſion ought to be for the Lords ſake, who hath ordained Magiſtracy and Government, for ſo ſaith St. <hi>Paul, the powers that be are ordained
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46060:16"/> of God; and whoſoever reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordinance of God.</hi> Likewiſe you may read the Doctrine of <hi>W. Tyndal,</hi> in his Book entitled, <hi>The Obedience of a Chriſtian man;</hi> and ſee how the bleſſed Martyrs eſpouſed and maintained the ſame delivered by the Apoſtles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XI.</head>
                  <p>NOW in order to give a right underſtanding, and that from plain mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, of the difference between the faith and practice of the Quakers, of the one part; and the faith and practice of the Chriſtians, in all ages, ſince the days of Chriſt, I have a purpoſe to ſet forth, as a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inſtance, the practice of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France:</hi> in regard they live under a Popiſh King, rather than the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and chiefly for this reaſon, beeauſe the Quakers are ſo prejudiced againſt our Clergy. Tho I believe, there is not ſounder men, nor a better diſciplined Church in the world; yet I ſay, they having always been ſo prejudiced againſt them, as to call them Beaſts, Dogs, <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, Witches, Devils, Antichriſts, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and a thouſand ſuch unchriſtian and horrible names; on purpoſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get an ill opinion in the people of them (as <hi>Burrough,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Fox</hi> his Myſtery confeſſeth) that ſo they might leave and forſake them: alſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering how frequently they have in their Books arraigned, impeached, and condemned the Magiſtracy of <hi>England,</hi> under the odious names of the Beaſt, which carry the Whore, the Perſecuters of Gods People, the Antichriſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That I think it more proper to take a foreign parallel, that, if poſſible, they may at laſt be brought to a confeſſion of their Errors, burn their Books, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Religion, and bethink themſelves where they have been, what they have been doing, and how ſcandalous their antimagiſtratical principles have been to the Chriſtian Religion: not that I have leiſure or parts to ſet forth this matter as it ought to be done; but am content to be as a Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Man to hew off the knots, and make the work fit for better Workmen, to compleat what I leave imperfect, and in order to this I ſhall abſtract ſome few paſſages of the 28th Synod held at <hi>Charenton</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> viz.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Acts of the</hi> 28 <hi>Synod of the Reformed Churches of</hi> France, <hi>aſſembled by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtys Permiſſion at</hi> Charenton, <hi>near</hi> Paris, <hi>on</hi> Monday <hi>the</hi> 26th <hi>day of</hi> December, 1644, <hi>and ended</hi> Thurſday <hi>the</hi> 26th <hi>of</hi> January 1645.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">See the Acts, Deciſions, and Decrees of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> per <hi>John Quick</hi> vol. 2. p. 425.</note>Firſt Monſieur <hi>Drelincourt</hi> opened the Seſſions with Prayer; and then the Lord Marquis of <hi>Clermont,</hi> General Deputy, preſented the Writ, given forth by his Majeſties Command, for calling the Synod, as followeth,
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <p>This day, being the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>February 1644.</hi> the King being then at <hi>Paris,</hi> upon the moſt Humble Petition of his Subjects of the pretended Reformed Religion, to permit them the calling and holding a National Synod, deſiring to gratify and treat favourably he ſaid Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cts, hath permitted, and doth permit them, the Convocation of a National Synod, next at <hi>Charenton;</hi> but with this condition, that they treat in it, of none other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46060:16"/> matters but of thoſe which be allowed them; and that the <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> whom his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall pleaſe <hi>to appoint</hi> be <hi>perſonally preſent</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Synod,</hi> as hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed. In witneſs whereof his Majeſty hath commanded me to iſſue out this Writ, which he hath ſigned with his own hand, and cauſed to be counter-ſigned by me his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and Secretary of State, and of his Commands.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Signed in the Original,</hi> Louis. <hi>And a little lower</hi> Phelippeaux.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </p>
                  <p>Aſſoon as the Officers of the Synod were choſen, the Lord <hi>Cumont,</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor for the King in his Council of State, and Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> deputed by his Majeſty, preſented Letters Patents, which did commiſſionate him to repreſent his Majeſty in this Synod; theſe being read were incerted into the Regiſter of the Acts of this Synod, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Louis <hi>by the Grace of God King of</hi> Navarre <hi>to our truſty Councellor in our Council of State and Court of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arliament gréeting.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>We having granted our Subjects of the pretended Reformed Religion to hold a National Synod in the Town of <hi>Charenton,</hi> near <hi>Paris,</hi> on the <hi>26th</hi> day of <hi>December</hi> next coming, compoſed of all the Deputies of the Provinces of our Kingdom, to treat of affairs concerning their Religion: And being to make choice of a meet perſon, and of approved fidelity to us, who may <hi>precide</hi> in the ſaid Aſſembly, as our Commiſſioner, and may <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent us</hi> in it, we have commiſſioned and deputed you, and we do commiſſionate and depute you, by theſe Preſents, ſigned with our own hand, to go unto the Town of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renton,</hi> and to <hi>ſit</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Synod there aſſembled,</hi> and to <hi>Repreſent</hi> our <hi>Royal Perſon in it;</hi> and to propoſe and determine whatever matters we ſhall give you in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, according to thoſe Memoirs and Inſtructions we have now delivered unto you: And you are to take <hi>héed</hi> that <hi>none</hi> other <hi>affairs</hi> be there debated, but <hi>ſuch</hi> as ought to be in thoſe Aſſemblies: And in caſe the Members of the ſaid Synod ſhould attempt to do any thing contrary thereunto, you ſhall hinder them, and interpoſe therein with our Authority, and to give us ſpeedy and timely notice of it, that ſuch courſe may be taken to prevent thoſe inconveniencies which would ariſe, as we ſhall judge moſt convenient: for the doing whereof we give you Power and Commiſſion, and Special Commandment by theſe Preſents. Given at <hi>Paris</hi> the <hi>28</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> in the Year of Grace <hi>1644,</hi> and of our Reign the ſecond.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Signed in the Original</hi> Louis, <hi>And a little lower</hi> Phelippeaux.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Speech of the Lord Commiſſioner unto the Synod, together with his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions made in their Majeſties Name,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Meſſieurs,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>As it is a very great honour to me to be commiſſionated by his Majeſty to aſſiſt in your Synod, and to acquaint you with his Will and Pleaſure; ſo alſo have I a great deal of joy and ſatisfaction to behold this illuſtrious Aſſembly, choſen out of all Provinces of this Kingdom: and that I can tell you by word of mouth, what was expreſly charged and commanded me by the King, and the Queen his Mother, which is to aſſure you of their good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46060:17"/> will unto you, and protection of you; and of all your Churches, and of the entire execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Edicts of Pacification, ſo long as you continue your ſelves within the bounds of your duty, ſubjection and fidelity which you owe unto their Majeſties; they being the Higher Powers, ſet over you by God, intruſted with the ſupream Authority; and your lot and portion being the honour of obedience to them, whereunto you ſtand obliged<note n="*" place="margin">I am the longer in this recital, that the Quakers may ſee; and in ſeeing may learn to know both their place and duty, both from Scripture, and the Practice of the Martyrs and all true Chriſtians, thro all Centuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </note> by your birth, the dictates of your Conſciences, and the favours you daily receive from their Majeſties; and by all kinds of conſideration both general and particular: and obſerve it, I beſeech you, as a ſingular mark of their Majeſties favour unto you, that there be of your Religion in the Kingdom<note n="†" place="margin">It was their obedience to the Laws brought them to that dignity: it is the diſobedience of the Quakers, and their antimagiſtratical principles, which keep them out of all places of truſt in the Government.</note> perſons of the higheſt quality, there be amongſt you moſt noble and illuſtrious Dukes and Peers, Mareſchals of <hi>France,</hi> Generals of Armies, Magiſtrates, and Judges in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Courts: and their Majeſties now, this very day, out of that great confidence they have in your Loyalty and Fidelity, have granted you this Aſſembly at the very Gates of the Metropolis of this Kingdom, in the very face and view of all <hi>France,</hi> and of this infinite people of <hi>Paris,</hi> vaſtly different from you in manners and humours, inclination and religion, who will be ſevere Witneſſes and Judges over all your actions.</p>
                        <p>And that all things may be done in that order preſcribed me by their Majeſties, I am in their Names commanded to acquaint you, That all Miniſters who are not natural born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but Strangers, are to be excluded this Synod; and that none may aſſiſt to vote in it who hath not Letters of Deputation from his Provincial Synod: and that during the time it be held you may have <hi>no communication with Foreigners,</hi> or other ſuſpected perſons; and foraſmuch as your Aſſemblies are not by any legal conſtitution a Body Politick, their Majeſties have <hi>forbidden</hi> you to meddle in <hi>State Affairs</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">Come <hi>G. W.</hi> look and learn, you are ſtrangers to theſe limitations, you have the face to abſolve his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects from their active obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Laws, which require them to pay Tyths, to pay to Church Wardens Rates, to take lawful Oaths, to carry Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which 'tis plain that as you increaſe the ſtrength of the Nation will decreaſe.</note> or matters of Juſtice, becauſe your Synod hath no power to judge of ſuch matters, but only to treat of points of Doctrine and Church Diſcipline.<note n="†" place="margin">
                              <hi>G. W.</hi> ſo do the Kings Laws forbid you, but whether you like the, <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, do regard thoſe Laws I ſhall ſhew by and by: no, the Law, what is the Law to you; for as <hi>G. Fox</hi> did not heed a Cart Load of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, no nor do you a Waggon Load of Laws.</note> Moreover their Majeſties do forbid you to <hi>print any Books</hi> in any place whatſoever, concerning your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whieh are not <hi>atteſted (<hi>i. e.</hi>
                           </hi> Licenced) by <hi>two</hi> Manual <hi>Certificates</hi> of <hi>two Miniſters</hi> at leaſt, under pain of Confiſcation of the whole Impreſſion: nor may you denounce any <hi>Excommunication</hi> againſt any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and others, who ſhall change their Religion for that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick, nor <hi>treat</hi> them <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully,</hi> neither by <hi>word</hi> nor <hi>writing.</hi>
                           <note n="†{inverted †}" place="margin">Hark <hi>G. W.</hi> then they were not to call ſuch Beaſts, Dogs, Wolves, Children of the Devil, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils incarnate, Enemies of all Righteouſneſs, Apoſtates, ſelf-condemned Apoſtates, as you have called me and others for our forſaking you, and conforming to the Religion Eſtabliſht.</note> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over when they ſpeak of the Pope they are not to call
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46060:17"/> him <hi>Antichriſt</hi>
                           <note n="†" place="margin">But you call both Miniſters and People, Parliaments and Magiſtrates, who either pay or receive Tythes Antichriſt: Oh hetrodox in all points, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </note>, nor to treat him diſreſpectfully; nor ſhall they tax the <hi>Roman</hi> Church with Idolatry, nor the Sacraments and Ceremonies thereof us humane Inventions and Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           <note n="*" place="margin">But you tell the Proteſtants their Sacraments are duſt, and that they roſe from the Pope, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And treat the Diſpencers thereof as Witches, Devils, Antichriſts, and what not, that is odious.</note> nor to make collections of Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>And now I come to ſhew you the Chriſtian Frame and Temper of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants in their Obedience to the Kings Commandment, by their Moderator, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>The Lord Commiſſioner having ended his Speech the Deputies returned their Anſwer by their Moderator Monſieur <hi>Garriſſoles.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Moderator's Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>WE thankfully acknowledge the great Goodneſs and Mercy of God Almighty, in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the Prayers of his poor Churches with his heavenly Bleſſing, and their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Condeſcention in accepting our moſt humble Petitions preſented by the Lords of our General Deputies, and granting us this Privilege of holding this Synod, and committing the <hi>Inſpection</hi> of it unto a perſon moſt illuſtrious for his Vertues, and well deſerving that high place of Dignity and Honour in the firſt and chiefeſt Parliament of the Kingdom; all theſe, and many other conſiderations more, do enforce our Souls with a ſweet and pleaſing violence, to break forth into enlarged Praiſes and enflamed Thankfulneſs, unto their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties; yea and in moſt ardent ſupplications unto our God for the preſervation of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred perſons, his Benediction upon their Government, the Glory of their Crowns, under whoſe comfortable Shadows the Churches enjoying a ſweet Peace will never have any other deſire or thought, than to practice faithfully and conſcientiouſly that moſt expreſs Command of our Lord and Saviour by his Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter, To fear God and honor the King;</hi> and that with a moſt entire and ſincere Obedience. And as we have no deſign to do it, ſo we ſhall never admit any perſon to ſit as a Member of our National Synod, who hath not a Deputation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor ſhall we hold any Correſpondency, nor receive any Letters coming from Foreigners,<note n="†" place="margin">See <hi>G. W</hi> the Quakers practice, and how different herein, as anon I ſhall ſhew.</note> nor return any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to them, unleſs that my <hi>Lord Commiſſioner,</hi> who repreſents his Majeſties perſon, ſhall have firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed them: nor will we debate about Matters of State, nor make any orders in relation to them;<note n="*" place="margin">Hark <hi>G. W.</hi> read your Edicts, and compare them, which reſemble theirs as black does white.</note> nor ſhall we ſet up Proivincial Councels in oppoſition to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties will: Nor, as his Majeſty hath demanded of us, will we ſuffer thoſe Canons of our National Synods, concerning the Approbation of Books that ſhall be printed on matters of Religion, to be violated,<note n="†" place="margin">See and behold an Example, the Proteſtants have regard to the Laws, the Quakers none.</note> nor ſhall we <hi>excommunicate</hi> any of thoſe perſons who quit the Communion of our Churches, for we do not arrogate to our ſelves any Juriſdiction over them
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46060:18"/> from that minute in which they left us; nor ſhall we tollerate any Sermons fraught with any injurious and reproachful Language againſt the Members of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whether in general or particular, nor ſuffer that Moneys be collected, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>From all which 'tis ſelf-evident from Scripture, Reaſon, and approved Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles commanded ſubjection and obedience to the higher powers; their Commands are poſitive, and not with a Proviſo, i. e. <hi>until you be convinced of this your duty,</hi> &amp;c. No they are Scripture Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and as ſuch ought to be obeyed; and ſo the Martyrs believed, and practiſed, and ſet examples: And you ſee how theſe worthy Chriſtians, the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, obeyed that wholſom doctrine; they did not anſwer the <hi>French</hi> King, that no Commands in Scripture are obliging, unleſs a man be firſt convinced, that what is there commanded ought to be obeyed; as <hi>Burroughs</hi> and <hi>Pen</hi> teach, and as the Quakers practice, who run counter to the practice of Chriſt, his Apoſtles, Martyrs, and all Chriſtians to this day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XII.</head>
                  <p>AND thus the Quakers may ſee, as in a Glaſs, That firſt the <hi>French</hi> King was humbly ſought by the Proteſtants, to grant them leave to hold a National Synod, upon which he anſwered their requeſt, provided firſt, that he might have a Commiſſioner in whom he could repoſe truſt and confidence to be reſident there, to hear and obſerve, that their diſcourſe did not tend to alienate the hearts of his Subjects from their obedience to him, as their King and Governor. Secondly, That they did not meddle with State matters, tending to beget diſobedience to the Laws of the Land, all which they as readily ſubmitted to: they promiſed they would not meddle with State matters, nor excommunicate and revile his Magiſtrates and Miniſters, nor hold a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with Strangers, to let other Nations eſpy the Faſhions and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of their Government, and thereby take meaſures againſt it; that they would obſerve his Laws in not printing Books without Licence, nor gather up Money to weaken the Subjects to carry on deſigns againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>But how far the Quakers differ in this point from the Chriſtian, both at home and abroad, I leave the Reader to judge, and that not from my bare ſay ſo, but from plain matter of fact. But ſtill to make it more plain, if more plain can be, I ſhall in a few inſtances ſet 1ſt. The <hi>French</hi> Kings method in commanding his Subjects. 2d. The manner of his Subjects Obedience and ready Compliance, altho not of his Perſwaſion, as to his Religion. 3d. The Quakers Practice and Principles relating to Government. 4th. Some brief Obſervations from the Premiſſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46060:18"/>
                  <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">French King.</note>YOu ſhall have no Communication with Strangers; you ſhall neither read Letters from them in your Convocation, nor return Letters to them, other than what my Commiſſioner approves of.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proteſt.</hi> Nor ſhall we read any Letters coming from Foreigners, nor return any Anſwer, unleſs my Lord Commiſſioner approve thereof, <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quak. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> Epiſtle to the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings of Friends in</hi>
                     </hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>or elſewhere from our yearly Meeting held in</hi> London, <hi>the</hi> v. vi vii <hi>and</hi> viii <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ys of the</hi> 4th <hi>month,</hi> 1693. <hi>p.</hi> 2. Several other Epiſtles from for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ign parts as <hi>Barbadoes, Maryland, Penſilvania, Virginia, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> were read, an Epiſtle from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland; Ja. Dickinſon,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Wilſon,</hi> at this Meeting gave an account of their Travels in <hi>Barbadoes, Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Jerſey, Penſilvania, Maryland, Virginia, New England, North Carolina, Rhoad Iſland, Long Iſland, Antego, Nevis, &amp;c.</hi> Four Epiſtles from <hi>Ireland,</hi> one from the laſt year Meeting in <hi>Dublin,</hi> another from <hi>Ulſter</hi> Province, another from <hi>Munſter</hi> Province, the fourth from <hi>Conought</hi> Province Meeting. An account was given of <hi>Dantzick</hi> friends. A Letter alſo from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> that there are a People rais'd up, and increaſed in <hi>Germany</hi> from among the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> called <hi>Pietiſts,</hi> by ſome called <hi>Quak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> perſecuted by the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> and the Prieſts, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our Friends Books have been ſpread amongſt them. Again <hi>p.</hi> 3. Friends appointed to view the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccounts, report</hi> that they find they are truly ſtated, and right kept; and friends are again adviſed to bring up with them the <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tal ſum</hi> of each <hi>Counties Collection.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Query did <hi>Wm. Crouch</hi> not forget the 5 <hi>l.</hi> he disburſed.</note> Again <hi>p.</hi> 4. the ſix friends of the City appointed and intruſted this Year with the accounts are, <hi>William Crouch, John Staploe, William Macket, William Chandler, William Beech, Nathaniel Marks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="observation">
                     <head>Obſervation.</head>
                     <p>Reader, A ſmall Remark will ſerve, 1ſt, 'Tis plain they hold a Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with, and receive Letters from Foreigners, return Anſwers, ſpread their Books into foreign parts, pretending to ſpread truth, as if the Scriptures were deficient. 'Tis alſo plain that they have a Fund or Bank, and a yearly Tax collected to maintain their Teachers, Travellers and Spies, both at home and abroad, ſee my Books <hi>Battering Rams againſt New Rome,</hi> &amp;c. p. 14. <hi>New Rome unm.</hi> p. 60. 'Tis alſo plain that they have Common Bankers with whom the keeping of the Exchequer is intruſted; their Names are, <hi>W. Crouch, J. Staploe, W. Macket, W. Chandler, W. Beech, Nath. Marks.</hi> See <hi>W. R.</hi>'s <hi>Second Scourge for</hi> G. Whitehead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on this Head.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:46060:19"/>
                  <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">French King.</note>YOu are not to meddle with State Affairs, or matters of Juſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Protest.</hi> Nor will we debate about State Affairs, or make any orders in relation to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King and Parl. of</hi> England. An Act of Parliament made the firſt year <hi>Gulielmi &amp; Mariae,</hi> intituled, <hi>An Act for exempting their Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects diſſenting from the Church of</hi> England, <hi>from the Penalties of certain Laws,</hi> &amp;c. Numb. 308.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Provided always that nothing herein contained ſhall be conſtrued to exempt any of the perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns aforeſaid from paying of Tythes, or other parochial duties, or any other duty to the Church or Miniſter, nor from any proſecution in any Eccleſiaſtical Court, or elſewhere for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Quakers Yearly Epiſt. p. 1. <hi>And therefore that all due and godly care be taken againſt the <hi>Grand Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>antichriſtian Yoak of Tythes,</hi> that our Teſtimony born, and greatly ſuffered for, be <hi>faithfully maintained againſt them</hi> in <hi>all reſpects,</hi> and againſt Steeple-houſe Rates; as alſo againſt the burden and impoſition of Oaths, that Friends at all their Monthly and Quarterly Meetings be reminded to call for the Records of Friends Sufferings, to ſee that they be duly gathered, truly entered, and kept, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſent up [to</hi> London] <hi>as hath been often adviſed, both of what Tythes are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be due, and for how long a time, and the time when taken, and by, and for whom; and what goods are taken [by diſtreſs for non-payment] and the value thereof; as well of thoſe <hi>not</hi> exceeding, as thoſe exceeding the ſums or quantities of Tythes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; it being a ſuffering in both for Truths ſake. They [the ſaid Monthly and Quarterly Meetings] being in theſe particulars found defective and imperfect in divers Counties, which is an obſtruction to the General Records of Friends Sufferings, and therefore the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings are deſired to take more care for the future, that <hi>all</hi> Friends Sufferings for truths ſake, may be brought up (to</hi> London) <hi>as <hi>full</hi> and <hi>compleat</hi> in <hi>all Reſpects</hi> as poſſibly may be. A complaint being made, that ſome that profeſs truth carry Guns in their Ships; 'tis therefore recommended to the Monthly and Quarterly Meetings to deal with them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <div type="observation">
                     <head>Obſervations.</head>
                     <p>Reader, the diſparity between the Quakers and the Chriſtians, in their practice, behaviour, gratitude and duty, is obvious. 1ſt. The <hi>French</hi> King commands his Subjects not to meddle with State Affairs: the Proteſtants with all complacency anſwer him no; they do not deſire it, neither will they ſo much as make orders about State matters, as not being their preſent ſtation, being Diſſenters from the Religion by Law eſtabliſhed. Thus you ſee the harmony of the <hi>French</hi> King and his Subjects, and ſo much for that: next you ſee in the firſt year of his preſent Majeſty, he, with the advice and conſent of his Parliament, indulged the Quakers the free exerciſe of their perſwaſion, from the penalty of poenal Statutes; but in the ſame Act for their Indulgence,
<pb facs="tcp:46060:19"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:46060:20"/>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:46060:20"/> there is a clauſe, as above told, which ratifies and confirms the payment of Tythes, and all Church dues, as firm as ever. In the next place you ſee what the Quakers ſay of it: They tell you, That Tythes are a <hi>grand oppreſſion,</hi> and not only ſo, but, which is worſe, an <hi>Antichriſtian Yoak;</hi> yea, ſuch a yoak, as that whoever receives or pays Tythes, does therein deny Chriſt to be come in the Fleſh by their doctrine: And thereupon by this Epiſtle, which is to go through <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and <hi>elſewhere,</hi> they warn their Diſciples to maintain their Teſtimony againſt the payment of Tythes <hi>in all reſpects:</hi> the like againſt Church-wardens Rates, and withal ſtoutly to oppoſe the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Oaths: Nay, this is not all yet, but being ſat in ſtate to hear the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of the Nation, there is a Complaint come up to the yearly Meeting, that ſome who profeſs truth <hi>(as if there were none who profeſs truth but the Quakers)</hi> carry Guns in their Ships: Well, they hear this Complaint, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that buſineſs to the Country Seſſions, I mean their Quarterly Meetings; for they have buſineſs of great moment; and thus, inſtead of thankfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the Governments kindneſs, they are privately undermining it, by alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the Kings Subjects from their active obedience to the known Laws of the Land; for this Epiſtle <hi>alias</hi> Edict is to go through <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>elſewhere,</hi> this <hi>elſewhere</hi> is through the world: for as <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis, whoſe Decrees reach to the ends of the earth, where <hi>Papiſts</hi> live, ſo is this yearly Meeting in <hi>London</hi> the <hi>Quakers</hi> Metropolis, and from thence goes forth their Law, which is obliging and binding as far as there are any Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers. And if any deſire to ſtay until they be convinced; <hi>Oh no!</hi> ſays <hi>W. Pen, away with this looſe plea, for it is a dangerous principle, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the true Religion: And which is worſe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">The Examin. and State of Lib. Spir. p. 3, 11. pr. 1681.</note> 
                        <hi>'tis the Root of Ranteriſm to aſſer that nothing is a duty incumbent upon thee, but what thou art perſwaded [or convinced] is thy duty, for the ſeared Conſcience pleads this liberty againſt all duty. The dark Conſcience is here unconcerned, the dead Conſcience is here uncondemned. I ſee no evil,</hi> ſays one, <hi>in paying Tythes to the hireling Prieſts; I ſee no evil,</hi> ſays another, <hi>in marrying by a Prieſt; I ſee no evil,</hi> ſays a third, <hi>in hiding in times of ſuffering, for I have</hi> Chriſt<hi>'s and</hi> Paul<hi>'s exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; I ſee no evil,</hi> ſays a fourth,<note place="margin">The <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves force their Apprentices to ſtand bare-headed before them in their Shops and Houſes, where they are Superiours. Oh Deceit and Hypocriſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>in putting off my Hat to my Superiors; I ſee no evil,</hi> ſays a fifth, <hi>in ſhutting up my Windows in obedience to authority, on</hi> Chriſtmas-day, <hi>or on Faſt-days, or other days ſet apart by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Thus, Reader, you may ſee the firſt capital ſins againſt the Quakers Commandments: and ſecondly, that they leave no room for their Diſciples to ſtay until they be convinced whether indeed theſe be ſins either in their own nature: or againſt the written word of God; or contained in the firſt or ſecond Table of the ten Commandments, oh no, they are tranſgreſſions againſt the Orders, Laws and Commands of <hi>Geo. Fox:</hi> And as ſuch, they are obliging upon all: whether conviction or no convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> behold the Doctrine of <hi>W. Pen:</hi> yea, the ſame <hi>William Pen</hi> that tells Mr. <hi>Faldo,</hi> That there is no Command in the Scripture farther obliging upon any mans Conſcience, than as he meets with a Conviction.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:46060:21"/>
                  <head>SECT. XV.</head>
                  <p> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obj."/> BUt poſſibly ſome may ſay, Indeed this yearly Epiſtle ſeems very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful in divers reſpects, and which deſerves conſideration; but what is the reaſon that the Chronicle and compendious Hiſtory do not come forth, that the Quakers have boaſted of near this thirty years, in their Book <hi>Judas and the Jews, &amp;c.</hi> p. 58. And their <hi>Rejoinder,</hi> p. 410. ſaying, <hi>Our faithful Chronicle of the bloody Tragedies of that profeſſing generation will tell <hi>future</hi> ages other things, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay, why <hi>future</hi> ages? This looks very odd, to tell us 20 or 30 years together of a compendious Hiſtory to come forth, of their faithful Chronicles to come out, and yet none is come forth to publick view:<note place="margin">No, they are ſadly dull, they begin to draw back.</note> what! do not the Quarterly and Monthly meetings carry up enough every year? or are they minded to reſerve it till all perſons concerned therein are dead and gone, and ſee none left to detect it? At that rate indeed they may tell <hi>future</hi> ages a lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſtory of cruel ſufferings; and little of it true, if any.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. As to the quarterly and monthly Meetings, tho they may be ſomewhat dull, and want quickening, yet no doubt but they have gathered up enough to print ſeveral volumes, for you ſee thay call for the whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, viz. <hi>Take <hi>more</hi> care for the <hi>future,</hi> that <hi>all</hi> friends <hi>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>erings</hi> may be brought up as <hi>full</hi> and <hi>compleat</hi> in all <hi>reſpects</hi> as <hi>poſſible</hi> may be, &amp;c.</hi> Thus we ſee what care they take firſt to magnifie themſelves by their great ſufferings, which in all the Hiſtory that I have read of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, I have not taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any thing of the like nature. 2. You may ſee by their threatned Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle how they intend to repreſent this Nation, as a perſecuting bloody-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed people: And knowing that great part of their ſufferings are ſhams, and nothing but noiſe, they are aſham'd (as well they may) to bring it forth. And to convince the World that it is ſo ſee my Book <hi>New Rome unmaskt, &amp;c.</hi> p. 54. where <hi>Samuel Cater</hi> of <hi>Littleport</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Ely,</hi> one of their preachers is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, for being recorded in their quarterly book for ſuffering a fine of 20<hi>l.</hi> for preaching at <hi>Plakenham</hi> in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> when indeed he was ſo far from loſing 20<hi>l.</hi> that he got 10<hi>l.</hi> into pocket (tho a rich man) in clear money: It's true, he was fined and his goods deſtrained, but never carried away, and in a little time every pennyworth returned, as 40 neighbours will witneſs; but this made ſuch a noiſe; and <hi>Sam</hi> being a right man for <hi>Fox,</hi> and as true to him as he was to <hi>Ja. Nayl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r,</hi> when he led his Horſe into <hi>Briſtol,</hi> he had 10 <hi>l.</hi> ſent him out of the publick Stock (Fund, Exchequer or Treaſury, or what you will call the Common Bank) by <hi>John Peacock,</hi> deceaſed, late of <hi>St. Ives,</hi> as a Reward for his Valour and Courage; but you muſt note he was a Preacher; for <hi>June</hi> 9. 1670. (which as my old Records ſtill by me tell me) there was a meeting at <hi>Littleport,</hi> where <hi>Sam. Fullig, Cl. Crabb, Tho. Hawks, Jo. Love, Henry Waddelow, Tho. Paine, R. Crabb,</hi> and others were fined, who had their Cows, Horſes, Mares, Pewter and Braſs taken away, but never any thing ſent them from <hi>London,</hi> nor their goods returned: But that which makes <hi>Sam. Cater</hi>'s Caſe ſtill
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46060:21"/> worſe, tho indeed I think there can be no greater cheat put upon future ages, yet this is more impudent, for <hi>anno</hi> 1679. <hi>S. Cater</hi> and <hi>Joſ. Harriſon</hi> put forth a Book entituled, <hi>A Lamentable Cry of Oppreſſion, &amp;c.</hi> In which Book the ſaid <hi>Sam.</hi> renews the memory of his ſufferings, for that meeting for which he did not ſuffer a groat, but got 10 <hi>l.</hi> clear into pocket, as I have ſaid, read p. 14. <hi>There being a meeting at</hi> Joſ. Harriſon's <hi>in</hi> Plakenham, July 2. 1670. <hi>And</hi> Sam. Cater <hi>being there, declaring the truth,</hi> W. Watts's <hi>his Wife came, and went and informed</hi> the Officers who came and had him before Chr. Colthorp, <hi>who ſaid he would fine</hi> Sam. 2O <hi>l. which accordingly he did, and ſent the Records of Conviction to</hi> Ely <hi>Magiſtrates, who ſent out their Warrants, and took away his goods, &amp;c.</hi> Thus ends the Relation, as to matter of fact, but he that writes a Hiſtory of that nature ſhould tell the whole truth, <hi>viz.</hi> Indeed I was ſo inform'd againſt, ſo fined, and deſtrained: <hi>But</hi> I had my goods again, this at leaſt he ſhould have ſaid, tho he had kept private his Reward of 10 <hi>l.</hi> which was purpoſely ſent him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But alas, he to make the world believe that he thus lamentably ſuffered under that lamentable Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Colthorp,</hi> nine years after the tranſaction was committed and done, and alſo to make the poor Quakers that heard him, and loſt their Fines without any reparation, believe that their Miniſter was zealous for the cauſe, a great ſufferer, yea, 20 <hi>l.</hi> thick, for coming to viſit them as a ſervant of the Lord, and a Meſſenger from the great God. He goes on, p. 44. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And now it is upon me, from the Lord to warn you all that have had any hand in oppreſſing his Children, and evil intreating his Servants and Meſſengers that he hath ſent amongſt you, to exhort you: But inſtead of receiving them and their Teſtimony, you have cauſed them</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Here <hi>Sam.</hi> thinks to blind the poor <hi>Quakers,</hi> and make them believe he was a 20 <hi>l.</hi> ſufferer, when he loſt not a groat.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſuffer: And them [alſo] that did receive them, and their Teſtimony: The Lord forgive you, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him that chuſes rather to ſuffer Affliction with the people of God, than to live in the pleaſures of this world. Sam. Cater.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have laid a ſnare for thee, and thou art taken, O <hi>Babylon;</hi> and thou waſt not aware; thou art found and alſo caught; put your ſelves in array againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> round about all you that bend the Bow, ſhoot at her, ſpare no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows; for the Lord hath opened his Armoury, and hath brought forth the weapons of his indignation, for this is the work of the Lord God of Hoſts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.14, 24, 25.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fr. King.</note>WE do forbid you to print any Books in any place whatſoever concerning Religion, which are not Atteſted [<hi>i. e.</hi> Licenſed] by two Manual Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates at leaſt, under pain of loſing the whole Impreſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prot.</hi> Nor as his Majeſty hath demanded of us, will we ſuffer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe Canons of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod concerning the Approbation [<hi>i. e.</hi> Licenſing] of Books, that ſhall be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d on matters of Religion to be violated; it being our ſincere and moſt fixed Reſolution to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erve in the preciſeſt and ſtricteſt manner their Majeſties Edicts; and under the benefit of them to l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:46060:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quak. Epiſt. ibid. p. 3.</hi> It's deſired that the monthly and quarterly meetings reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively takes notice of all Friends Books that are or may be ſent to them, according to former agreement, and take care for the diſperſing the ſame for the ſervice of Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and take care to adviſe the Correſpondents for the Counties to write only to your Correſpondents in <hi>London</hi> about their ſufferings, leſt their ſuffering caſe be delayed.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>Renewed advice to the reſpective Monthly and Quarterly Meetings in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and for the preſerving and ſpreading Friends Books, for Truths ſervice.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>THeſe are to let you underſtand that our Friends have at ſeveral yearly Meetings had under their ſerious conſideration, hw all thoſe Books that are printed for the ſervice of Truth and the unity of Friends, might moſt effectually be ſpread, for a general ſervice to Truth, and Information unto Friends and others: And at the laſt yearly Meeting it was left unto this meeting, who have ſettled as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That thoſe that print friends books, ſhall the firſt opportunity after printed, within one month at moſt, ſend to one of the Correſpondents in the ſeveral Counties, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>For each Monthly Meeting two Books of a ſort if under Sixpence, and one of a ſort if above Sixpence, for theſe reaſons.</p>
                        <p n="1">
                           <hi>1.</hi> For Friends to have general notice of what Books are printed.</p>
                        <p n="2">
                           <hi>2.</hi> That they may ſend for what other quantities they may ſee a ſervice for.</p>
                        <p n="3">
                           <hi>3.</hi> That the Printer may be encouraged in printing for friends.</p>
                        <p n="4">
                           <hi>4.</hi> That one Book, at leaſt, of a ſort, that ſhall be printed [except Collections] may be kept in each Monthly and Quarterly Meeting, for the ſervice of Friends and Truth, as there ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ccaſion for the future.</p>
                        <p n="5">
                           <hi>5.</hi> It's agreed that the Printer will allow two pence in the ſhilling for all ſuch Books.</p>
                        <p n="6">
                           <hi>6.</hi> It's Agreed, That ſome here ſhall be appointed to examine the Printer, to ſee that they ſend no Books, but ſuch as are appointed by Friends.</p>
                        <p n="7">
                           <hi>7.</hi> It's Agreed and Adviſed, that the Printers account be fully cleared once a year at leaſt, by thoſe Friends the Country ſhall ſend up to the yearly Meeting.</p>
                        <p n="8">
                           <hi>8.</hi> It's Agreed, That the name of the Printer imployed by Friends ſhould be ſent, with directions how to write to him.</p>
                        <p>Dear Friends and Brethren, it's tenderly adviſed and recommended to you, that you be careful and diligent in the ſpreading of all ſuch Books that are printed for the ſervice of Truth, and are written either in defence of it, or <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Holy profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or by way of <hi>Epiſtle, Warning, Caution, Exhortation,</hi> or <hi>Prophecy;</hi> that ſo we may not be remiſs or negligent in promoting the holy truth, that nothing may be wanting on our parts to promote it, and the ſpreading of it; that the Nations may be informed, and brought into the knowledge of it; that in the end we may give an account with joy. An ancient friend, the Printers name is as follows, to whom direct thus: For <hi>Andrew Soale,</hi> at the <hi>Crooked Billet</hi> in <hi>Holy-well-lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> Or to <hi>Thomas Northcoat,</hi> at his Shop in <hi>George-yard, in Lombard-ſtreet, London.</hi> And this we think needful you ſhould record in your Quarterly Books, and ſometimes read it for rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mbrance and notice. Signed in the behalf of the Meeting the 18th of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>th m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nth, <hi>1693.</hi> by <hi>Benjamin Bealing.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:46060:22"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>The yearly Meeting Epiſtle, the 27th of the 3d month, 1675.</hi> It is our Senſe, Advice, Admonition and Judgment, in the fear of God, and the authority of his Power and Sprit, to Friends and Brethren in their ſeveral Meetings, that no ſuch ſlight and contemptible names and expreſſions, as calling men and womens Meetings, Courts, Seſſions or Synods: that they are Popiſh Impoſitions, uſeleſs and burthenſome: And that faithful Friends Papers which <hi>we</hi> Teſtifie, have been given forth by the Power and Spirit of God, are mens Edicts or Canons, or embracing them, bowing to men Elders in the ſervice of Truth, Popes and Biſhops, with ſuch ſcornful ſayings be permitted among them: But let Gods power be ſet upon the top of that unſavoury Spirit, and them that uſe it.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed by <hi>George Whitehead, William Pen,</hi> and others.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am the larger in this Citation, to convince the world that the Quakers prefer their own Books before and above the Scripture, contrary to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in their ſheet they delivered to the Parliament: as alſo to ſhew the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of ſome amongſt them, that tell people they have no Epiſtles read amongſt them, as</hi> Francis Bugg <hi>ſets forth; which I know they can no more be ignorant of, than of the Suns ſhining at noon-day: And in order to a further diſcovery thereof, I ſhall recite the Titles of ſome of their Epiſtles, as I did in</hi> New Rome Arraigned, <hi>p. 41. which to this day they have not denyed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Two General Epiſtles to the Flock of God, where-ever they are diſperſed, by <hi>M. Fell</hi> and <hi>J. Park, printed 1664.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> To Friends <hi>in England, Ireland, Scotland, Holland, New England, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes,</hi> or any where elſe where the Lord ſhall order this to come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> A General Epiſtle to be read in the fear of God in the Aſſembly of his people, by <hi>W. D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> The word of the Lord to <hi>Syon</hi> the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> the Bride, the Lambs Wife, the excellency of all the Glory that is amongſt the people, by <hi>W. D.</hi> printed <hi>1664.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. An Epiſtle to Friends every where, to be read diſtinctly in their Meetings, by <hi>K. W.</hi> printed <hi>1681.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> All Friends every where, this is the word of the Lord unto you all; this you may read amongſt the children of the light, and of the day, per <hi>G. Fox.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> This is only to go amongſt Friends.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> An Epiſtle to Friends in <hi>England</hi> to be read in their Aſſemblys.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9. An Epiſtle to the Remnant of Friends</hi> per G. Whitehead, <hi>concluding thus,</hi> Let this be read diſtinctly in the life and authority of God (from whence it came) among Friends, in and about the City of <hi>London,</hi> and elſewhere, as any Friends are moved in the ſame Life.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> To all people who meet in Steeple-houſes in <hi>England,</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>p. 2.</hi> A meſſage from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in <hi>England,</hi> or elſewhere, into all the Steeple-houſes to be read.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11.</hi> To the Children of Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I deſire this Epiſtle may be read in your ſeveral Meetings, <hi>William Pen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Several papers given forth for the ſpreading of truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I charge you in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord God to ſend this [Epiſtle] among Friends and Brethren every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be read, in all Meetings, to you all, this is the word of the Lord God, <hi>Geo. Fox.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:46060:23"/>
                  <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
                  <p>HAving in the foregoing Section proved from plain matter of fact, that the Quakers prefer their nonſenſical Pamphlets before the Scriptures, being compared with the contemptible expreſſions they give them, as beaſtly ware, death, duſt, and ſerpents meat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> notwithſtanding their Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Sheet they delivered to the Parliament, and as a proof it will ſtand againſt them beyond all their gloſſing; I think I need to make no other Remark or Obſervation, having largely ſhewed their practice from their own works, and therefore I come now to anſwer an Objection, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Poſſibly ſome may ſay, that tho they take the liberty of the Preſs to ſpread their Heretical Doctrine, and defamatory Libels, as the <hi>Battledoor for the Magiſtrates, Teachers, and Profeſſors,</hi> in the form and figure of a Childs penny horn book, to learn the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <hi>tu</hi> and <hi>vos.</hi> As likewiſe their <hi>Primmer</hi> put out by <hi>G. Fox</hi> (formerly a Journeyman Shoemaker) containing 2434 Queries, as what is a <hi>Noun,</hi> a <hi>Pronoun,</hi> a <hi>Participle,</hi> an <hi>Adverb, &amp;c.</hi> as at large recited by me in my book <hi>Battering Rams againſt New Rome,</hi> &amp;c. p. 16, 17. yet they often pretend to moral vertues; and they pretend they do not hinder the Sale of your Books, as in <hi>W. Pens</hi> Rejoinder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> part 2. p. 404. <hi>I do aver</hi> (ſays <hi>W. Pen</hi> in the name of the Quakers) <hi>we never endeavour any ſuch thing as to prevent the ſale of an Adverſaries Books: Therefore, in ſo many words, they [who ſay we do] have certified an abſolute Lye,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now for proof that the Quakers do hinder the Sale of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Books, I will give you three inſtances, whereby it will appear, how falſe <hi>William Pen</hi> is in this caſe, as well as in many more that might be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; but what will they not ſay for holy Church. Oh the deceit, the fraud, and religious cheats that are to be found amongſt the Teachers of this people: but as he himſelf obſerves in a little Pamphlet of his ſtiled, <hi>A Brief Anſwer to a falſe and fooliſh Libel,</hi> &amp;c. p. 25. <hi>But the truth is, error can only be maintained by error.</hi> And what can we expect from <hi>W. Pen,</hi> who has vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated as groſs Idolatry wrote by <hi>Joſ. Coal</hi> to <hi>G. Fox,</hi> as ever <hi>Muggleton</hi> uttered, in his Book <hi>Judas and the Jews,</hi> &amp;, c. p. 44 to 47. I ſay what can we expect of ſuch men as <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Whitehead</hi> who will ſay and unſay, this to day and that to morrow, and by and by ſtand to neither? well but let me proceed to prove <hi>W. Pen</hi> a Lyer for once, ſince he avers in the name of the Quakers, that they never hinder the Sale of their Adverſaries Books, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="instance">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Inſtance</hi> 1.</head>
                     <p>About the year 168<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>William Rogers</hi> put forth a Book againſt the <hi>Foxonian</hi> Quakers Uſurpation of their Womens Meetings, &amp;c. intituled, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker diſtinguiſhed from the Apoſtate and Innovate, in five parts.</hi> This Book <hi>John Barnard</hi> a diſſenting Quaker ſold, and for which thing <hi>only</hi> they excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46060:23"/> him, as at large ſet forth in my Book <hi>de Chr. Lib. &amp;c.</hi> part 2. p. 179. An Abſtract thereof I ſhall recite, viz. <hi>From the monthly meeting at</hi> Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire-houſe, <hi>the</hi> 4th <hi>of the</hi> 11th <hi>month,</hi> 1681. <hi>Whereas there have been ſome unruly Spirits gone out from the truth, and the unity of the bleſſed power of God, writing, print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and publiſhing things hurtful to truth, by <hi>corrupting</hi> of peoples <hi>minds,</hi> tending alſo to draw them into diſeſteem</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Mark the two things this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication are bottomed upon, <hi>viz.</hi> firſt corrupting of peoples minds, next tending to weaken the eſteem the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Quakers have of ſuch Deceivers.</note> 
                        <hi>of many of the Lords Servants; we find our ſelves concerned to take notice of ſome of this kind befaln</hi> Jo. Barnard, <hi>formerly a member of this Meeting, who hath diſperſed into ſeveral parts of this Nation divers of thoſe <hi>perni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ks</hi> in print, wrote by</hi> W. Rogers, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> The Chriſtian Quaker diſtinguiſhed from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and Innovater: <hi>So that now we being wholly clear, having uſed an utmoſt endeavour to reclaim him do not only T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtifie againſt that <hi>Spirit,</hi> which hath led him into that diſorderly practice, but alſo againſt <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>i</hi> while joyned thereunto; nor can we have <hi>Spiritual communion</hi> or <hi>fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> with him, until unfeignedly he ſhall return unto the truth, by condemnation of that Work and Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>By which 'tis plain that the Quakers do endeavour to hinder the Sale of their Adverſaries Books: as this excommunication out of their Fellowſhip and Spiritual Communion, for ſelling the ſaid Book, is an evidence and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="instance">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Inſtance</hi> II.</head>
                     <p>Whereas <hi>G. Keith</hi> wrote ſeveral Books againſt the errors of the Quakers in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> and for which they perſecuted him, as their Book ſtiled <hi>The Tryals of</hi> Peter Boſs, George Keith, Tho. Budd <hi>and</hi> William Bradford, <hi>before a Court of Quakers at the Seſſions held at</hi> Philadelphia <hi>in</hi> Penſilvania, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at large ſet forth: But the ſaid <hi>Geo. Keith</hi> coming into <hi>England</hi> was examined by the yearly meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>June</hi> 1694. Where they adviſed <hi>G. Keith</hi> in theſe words; <hi>And therefore it is the tender Advice and Counſel, that</hi> Geo. Keith <hi>ſhould either call in theſe Books, or at leaſt publiſh ſomething effectually to clear the body of the people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Quakers, <hi>and their Miniſters, from thoſe groſs errors charged on ſome few in</hi> America, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This continued until <hi>May</hi> 1695. And <hi>G. Keith</hi> not calling in his Books, nor clearing the body of the <hi>Quakers</hi> from thoſe groſs errors which <hi>G. K.</hi> had charged on them, they excommunicated the ſaid <hi>G. Keith, May</hi> 17. 1695. <hi>As acted by an unchriſtian Spirit: and it is the ſenſe and judgment of this méeting</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that the ſaid</hi> Geo. Keith <hi>is gone from the Bleſſed unity of the peaceable ſpirit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and hath thereby ſeparated himſelf from the holy fellowſhip of the Church of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </hi> Which is as large an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication as the Pope himſelf or his Infallible Council ever pretended to; for they have not only by their Bull of Excommunication cut him off (as they dream) from the fellowſhip of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>London, Wales, &amp;c.</hi> but off from the whole Church of Chriſt: And as this is a great arrogancy in the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and preſumption too, ſo do they thereby differ from the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46060:24"/> And in regard this their Bull of Excommunication was denounced againſt <hi>G. Keith,</hi> for that he did not effectually call in his Books writ againſt the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and thereby clear the body of the <hi>Quakers</hi> from thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors charged upon the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Penſilvania:</hi> which in Conſcience he could not do, in regard he knew them Guilty thereof: This is a plain demonſtration that <hi>W. Pen</hi>'s averring that they never endeavour to hinder the ſale of their Adverſaries Books, is a great untruth. See the next proof.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="instance">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Inſtance</hi> III.</head>
                     <p>In the year 1693. I put forth a Book entituled, <hi>New Rome Arraigned, &amp;c.</hi> which the <hi>Quakers</hi> by an Officer ſeized, and carried 60 of them to a <hi>Quakers</hi> houſe, and Indicted me in the <hi>Old Baily, London.</hi> An Abſtract of the ſaid Bill of Indictment is as followeth.</p>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <p>
                              <hi>London ſſ.</hi> At the General Quarter Seſſions of the Peace holden for the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> of the ſaid City, on <hi>Monday</hi> the ninth of <hi>October, 1693.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>J. F.</hi> Knight, Mayor of the ſaid City; Sir <hi>P. W.</hi> Kt. Sir <hi>J. M.</hi> Kt. Aldermen; Sir <hi>S. L.</hi> Recorder of the ſaid City; the King and Queens Juſtices, to hear and determine the tranſgreſſions of Felons, and other enormities committed within the ſaid City: The ſame Seſſions is adjourned by the foreſaid Juſtices, until <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of the ſame month of <hi>October, 1693.</hi> at <hi>7</hi> of the clock in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> forenoon, at <hi>Juſtice-hail</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily, London,</hi> to be holden before the foreſaid Juſtices and their Aſſociates, according to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>And now paſſing by moſt of the form, I come to ſet forth the Aggravating terms of their ſaid Indictment,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Ut ſupra:</hi> A certain Bill of Indictment againſt one <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> then and there brought before <hi>B. B. G. B,</hi> &amp;c. Jury-men, then and there ſworn and charged to enquire for the ſaid King and Queen, and the body of the ſaid City: And was returned by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thus Indorſed, <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> Which Bill follows in theſe words: The Jury for our Lord the King and Queen do preſent upon their Oaths, That <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> late of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> Yeoman, being a perſon of an <hi>unquiet</hi> and <hi>turbulent</hi> diſpoſition; <hi>deviſing, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> and intending <hi>falſly, unlawfully, ſeditiouſly</hi> and <hi>maliciouſly, <hi>Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, Ja. Park, Ben. Antrobus, Sam. Waldenfeild, &amp;c.</hi>
                              </hi> faithful Subjects of our Lord and Lady the King and Queen, now of this their Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> extremely to ſcandalize; to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> and bring to Infamy and Reproach amongſt their Neighbours, and other Subjects of our ſaid King and Queen: As alſo to <hi>move, ſtir up,</hi> and cauſe <hi>diſcords, tumults</hi> and <hi>miſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                                    <desc>•••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſlaughters</hi> between the Subjects of this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> on the 18th day of <hi>September</hi> in the 5th year of our Lord and Lady, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And upon divers other days and times, as well before as after, at <hi>London</hi> aforeſaid (to wit) in the Pariſh Church<note n="*" place="margin">Tis not a Steeple-houſe it ſeems now, however neither I nor the Quakers wear there.</note> of St. <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> in <hi>Farringdon</hi>-Ward, he <hi>falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>y, maliciouſly, ſeditiouſly</hi> and <hi>illegally</hi> made, compoſed and printed, publiſhed and diſperſed amongſt the Subjects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a certain <hi>ſcand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>ous, mal cious</hi> and <hi>defaming</hi> Libel, againſt the ſaid <hi>G. Whitehead,</hi> &amp;c. — The ſame <hi>Engliſh</hi> Book or Pamphlet not being firſt Entered in the Regiſter-book of the Cmpany of Stationers of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46060:24"/>
                              <note n="*" place="margin">No more do the Quakers.</note> of <hi>London,</hi> and alſo not being Lycenced by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,<note n="†" place="margin">Why does not <hi>G. W</hi> get his Books Lycenced by Act of Parliament.</note> Proclamation, or added to the Book (this may be Printed) by vertue of any Warrant under the Seal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or one, or both the principal Secretaries of State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor Lycenced,<note n="*" place="margin">I hope the Quakers will Lycence their Meetting-houſes, now they thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely perſecute me for not Lyce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>cing my Book. <hi>Canes timidi vehementius latrant.</hi>
                              </note> nor Authoriſed by any perſon whatſoever, againſt the form of the Statute in that caſe lately made and provided, to the bad example of all that ſhall offend in that caſe, and againſt the Peace of our Lord and Lady the King and Queen, their Crown and Dignity.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>Ignoramus. <hi>Goodfellow.</hi>
                                 </hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>Reader, I have tranſcribed enough to ſhew their indicting me, and that for no other crime than not Lycencing my Book: If they ſay I put up a mock-Pillory, to ſhew what they in reality deſerved, who, as in the ſame Book I have ſet forth, offered to ſuffer, as in the caſe of Perjury, if they falſify their word, which they did do, in the Caſe of Evidence, and that in the Name of the Lord, which amount to an Oath. But ſuppoſe the form of a Pillory was not eaſy to them, muſt I therefore be tried and judged to move, <hi>ſtir up,</hi> cauſe <hi>diſcords, tumults,</hi> and <hi>miſerable ſlaughters,</hi> &amp;c. Well however, as this ſhews what the Quakers would do had they power, ſo it is a ſufficient proof that they did endeavour to hinder the Sale of my Books; alſo this their indicting me ſhows, what an envious and lying ſpirit they, <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> and his Brethren, are of.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
                  <p>AS I have ſhewed how contrary the Principles and Practices of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, are to the Principles and Practices of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, and indeed to all other Chriſtians, I am now about to ſhew their diſparity in the Articles of their Faith; ſetting forth an Abſtract of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants Confeſſion of Faith, containing 40 in number, which was preſented to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>French</hi> Kings, as judging it a moſt proper way to obtain their Liberty; as at large in the 1ſt Volume of <hi>J. Quicks</hi> Hiſtory ſtiled, <hi>Synodicon in Galia Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formata,</hi> p. 6. to 15. And likewiſe what the Quakers believe, if they believe as they write; for by reaſon they have not given forth diſtinct Articles of their Faith like the Chriſtian Churches in all ages, I muſt collect ſome ſelect paſſages out of their Books in one Column, and the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="quaker" type="part">
                              <head>The Quakers Faith.</head>
                              <p>A Declaration to all the world of our Faith, and what we believe who are called Quakers.</p>
                              <div type="part">
                                 <pb n="42" facs="tcp:46060:25"/>
                                 <head>Concerning God and Chriſt.</head>
                                 <p>Burrows <hi>works, p. 439.</hi> We believe there is one only true God, who is a Spirit, and his preſence filleth heaven and earth, and he is eternal and everlaſting, the Creator and Preſerver of all things.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>Sauls Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 8.</hi> He that hath the ſame ſpirit that raiſed up Jeſus from the dead is equal with God.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>The Sandy Foundation, p. 12, 16.</hi> The vulger do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſatisfaction being dependent on the Second Perſon of the imagined Trinity of diſtinct perſons in the unity of Eſſence <hi>Refuted.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>The Sword of the Lord drawn,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 5.</hi> Your imagined God beyond the Stars, and your carnal Chriſt is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denied, and teſtified againſt by the light: to ſay, that Chriſt is God and Man in one perſon is a Lye.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>A Queſtion to Profeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 20, 27, 33.</hi> To whom do the Names <hi>Jeſus</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> chiefly and in the firſt place belong; do they belong to the body which was took by him, or to him who took the body? Is not the <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ſtance,</hi> the <hi>Life,</hi> the <hi>Anointing</hi> called Chriſt where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ver it is found? doth not the Name [Chriſt;] belong to the whole body, and every member in the body as <hi>well</hi> as to the <hi>dead.</hi> Now the Scriptures do expreſly diſtinguiſh between Chriſt and the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he wore, between him that came, and the body in which he came; between the ſubſtance which was vailed, and the vail that vailed it; [Lo I come, a body haſt thou prepared me] there is plainly <hi>he,</hi> and the body in which <hi>he</hi> came; there is the outward veſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>l, and the inward life; this we certainly know, and can <hi>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>er</hi> call the <hi>bodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>arment Chriſt,</hi> but that which appeared and dwelt <hi>in</hi> the body, <hi>&amp;c. Thus do they deny Chriſt which the Apoſtles preached, ſaying,</hi> Acts <hi>5.30, 35.</hi> The God of our fathers raiſed up Jeſus, whom ye ſlew and hanged on a tree, him hath God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted with his right hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give repentance to Iſrael, and forgiveneſs of ſins. <hi>Acts 2.36.</hi> Therefore let all the houſe of Iſrael know aſſuredly that God hath made the ſame Jeſus, whom ye crucified, both Lord and Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </p>
                              </div>
                           </div>
                           <div n="christian" type="part">
                              <head>The Chriſtians Faith.</head>
                              <p>WE believe and confeſs there
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46060:25"/> is but one God only, whoſe being only is ſimple, ſpiritual, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, inviſible, immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, infinite, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible: And that the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture teacheth us, that in that one ſimple di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine being there be three perſons ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; the Father, to wit, the firſt cauſe in order and the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all things; the Son, his everlaſting word; the Holy Ghoſt, his vertue, power, and efficacy: the Son be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Father from everlaſting; the Holy Ghoſt from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting proceeding from the Father and the Son; theſe 3 perſons are not confounded but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, and yet not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, but of one and the ſame eſſence, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, power and equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and to conclude, we allow of that which thoſe four ancient Councils have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; and we deteſt all other Sects and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies condemned by thoſe holy Doctors, St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> St. <hi>Hillary,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> and St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:46060:25"/>
                  <p>Now if the Light only be Chriſt, and as they ſay, they can never call the Body Chriſt, then are the Apoſtles found falſe Witneſſes, and the Quakers acquit <hi>Judas</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> for they never did hang the Light or Spirit upon a Tree, they never Crucified the Light; ſee <hi>Quakeriſm wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and Chriſtianity reviving,</hi> &amp;c. p. 15 to 30, for more of this. <hi>Will. Bayley</hi>'s Works, p. 300, 307. He being asked, What Body Chriſt hath, and where is it, ſeeing its ſaid to be at the Right hand of God, he replies ſaying,
<q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div n="quaker" type="part">
                                 <p>A [Body] haſt [thou] prepared [me] <hi>mark the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> [thou] [me] and [a body.] This [me] that ſpake in the [body] was the [Chriſt.] <hi>Again, p. 307.</hi> For they [his Diſciples loved his perſon for the ſake of the frame and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Spir t that dwelt in him, or elſe what was his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to them m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>re than another perſon, but for [the ſake of] that which dwelt in him they loved him.</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <hi>The Chriſt. Qua. and his Dev. Teſt. p. 98.</hi> The Se-pent is a Spirit, now nothing can bruiſe the head of the Serpent but ſomething that is Spiritual, as the Serpent is; but if that body of Chriſt were the ſeed, then could he not bruiſe the Serpents head in all, becauſe the body of Chriſt is not ſo much as in any one: And conſequently the ſeed of the promiſe is an holy principle of Light and Life, that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the heart bruiſeth the Serpents head: And becauſe the Seed, which <hi>cannot</hi> be that <hi>body,</hi> is the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                                          <desc>••</desc>
                                       </gap>iſt,</hi> as ſaith the Scripture, the <hi>Séed</hi> is one, and that <hi>Séed</hi> is <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <div type="part">
                                    <head>Touching the Scriptures.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Geo. Whitehead's Serious Apology, p. 46.</hi> That which is ſpoken from the ſpirit of Truth in any, is of as great Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as the Scriptures and Chapters are and greater. <hi>G. W.s Iſhmael, p. 10.</hi> That which is written is the Letter, which is death and killeth.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Saul's Errand to Dam. &amp;c. p. 7.</hi> All that do ſtudy to raiſe a living thing out of a dead, to raiſe the Spirit out of the Letter are Conjurers; the Letter of the Scripture is death and killeth.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Several Petitions anſwered, p. 30.</hi> If ever you own the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, you will own our Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, which are given forth by the ſame power and ſpirit.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Truths Defence, p. 2, 102.</hi> You might have as well condemned the Scriptures to the fire, as our Writings, for our giving forth Papers and Printed Books, it is from the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate eternal Spirit of God.</p>
                                    <pb n="44" facs="tcp:46060:26"/>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>The Quakers Refuge fixed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 17.</hi> Whether the firſt Penman of the Scriptures was <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Hermes,</hi> or whether both theſe are not one; or whether there are not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny words contained in the Scriptures which were not ſpoken by Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit; whether ſome words were not ſpoken by the Grand Impoſtor, ſome by wicked men, ſome by wiſe men ill applied, ſome by good men ill expreſſed, ſome by falſe Prophets, and yet true; ſome by true Prophets, and yet falſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Davids Enemies diſcovered,</hi> &amp;c. per G. Whitehead <hi>and</hi> Chriſtopher Atkinſon, <hi>p. 7.</hi> And theſe [the Apoſtles] do not call the Letter the Rule; and the four Books <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> the New Teſtament and Goſpel, as thou, and thy generation [the Prieſts] do, and thy Miniſtry is in the Letter which killeth.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>News coming up,</hi> &amp;c. per G. Fox, <hi>p. 14.</hi> Your Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal is carnal, <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin;</hi> and your word is carnal, the letter and the light is carnal, the letter and your Baptiſm is carnal, and your Sacrament is carnal, and their Communion is carnal: A little Bread and Wine, ſo duſt is the Serpents meat; their original is but duſt, which is but the letter which is death; their Church is duſt, ſo the Serpent feed upon duſt; and their Goſpel is duſt, <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> which is but the letter.</p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div type="part">
                                    <head>Touching Ordinances.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>P. 34.</hi> A voice and a word to all you Deceivers who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people, and Blaſphemers who utter forth your Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and Hypocriſy, that tell people of a Sacrament, and tell them it is the Ordinance of God; bluſh, bluſh. and tremble, before the Lord God Almighty, you who live in the Witchery, and bewitch the people, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Burroughs Works about Water Baptiſm, p. 518.</hi> We do utterly deny, and do ſay it is no Ordinance of God, but it is an Inſtitution of the Whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it by a popiſh Inſtitution, and your practice of it is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and no part of the Worſhip of God, <hi>p. 51.</hi> have you been bewitched from the ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>dience of the truth <hi>within</hi> to obey the <hi>Letter without.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Will. Smiths Primmer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 36. Queſt.</hi> How is it concerning theſe things called Ordinances, as Baptiſm, and Bread and Wine? <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to thoſe things they aroſe from the <hi>Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>s</hi> Invention, who hath had power in the night of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, and hath ſet up his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>es which are yet continued in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46060:26"/> 
                                       <hi>England,</hi> tho he ſeemingly is denied; and the whole practice of thoſe things as they uſe them, had their Inſtitution by the Pope, and were never ſo ordained of Chriſt. <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may I know when Chriſt is truly preached? <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that are falſe [Miniſters] preach Chriſt without, and bid people believe in him, as he is in heav n ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ve; but they that are Chriſts Miniſters preach Chriſt within.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>See my Sheet to the Parliament,</hi> p. <hi>5.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>A Muſick Lecture,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 25.</hi> For where they are I was in Performances, in Ordinances, in Family Duties, in Hearing, in Reading, in Faſting; but when I came to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>nd my mind to that of God in me, then I began to learn to be a Fool, inſomuch that I durſt not give thanks for the victuals that were ſet before me.</p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div type="part">
                                    <head>Concerning Election and Reprobation.</head>
                                    <p>Truths Defence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 92. <hi>We [Quakers] are elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Salvation, we have the witneſs within us, praiſed be God who hath elected and choſen us before the foundation of the world: but thou [the Prieſt] art ordained of old for Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and for Perdition among the ungodly ones, and art a Reprobate one that hates Chriſt and art blind.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>Reader, I have at large proved out of their Books, that all Miniſters that ſprinkle Children with Water, all that preach Chriſt without, as he is in Heaven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, at the right hand of God; all that take a Text, and preach out of the Scriptures; all that either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or pay Tythes, as at large in my <hi>Second Summons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8. And now I am willing to give you the Quakers Faith and Perſwaſion concerning them, as in their Book, <hi>A brief Diſcovery of a threefold Eſtate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 7, 8. with the ſame Title ſet thus over their heads, <hi>viz.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div type="part">
                                    <head>Of the falſe Miniſtry.</head>
                                    <p>The Prieſts of the world are <hi>1.</hi> Conjurers, raiſing dead Doctrine out of the letter, which is death, raiſing death out of death, notable Conjurers. <hi>2.</hi> Thieves and Robbers. <hi>3.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſts, the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> cannot ſhew any Scripture for their heatheniſh ways and beaſtial worſhips. <hi>4.</hi> Witches, blind Guides. <hi>5.</hi> Devils, the Serpent is head in them. <hi>6.</hi> Liers, the Commiſſion and Call of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts come from <hi>Oxford</hi>
                                       <pb n="46" facs="tcp:46060:27"/> and <hi>Cambridge.</hi> A poyſonous-fountain, the <hi>Sir Symons</hi> of the age, run to <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> they run with <hi>Simon.</hi> Theſe are not Miniſters of Chriſt, but Stewards of the Devils Magazines, Diſſemblers and Liers. <hi>7.</hi> A viperous and ſerpentine generation going about to murder the Child Jeſus, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>lding a worm-eaten beaſtly form. <hi>8.</hi> Blaſphemers, yea, of the Devil, fearful Blaſphemers. <hi>9.</hi> Scarlet coloured Beaſts, a Harlot full of abomination and filthineſs. <hi>10. Babilons</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, ſelling beaſtly ware for a large price, <hi>the Letter</hi> which is <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ſt</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> the day is coming when theſe Idol Merchants, theſe coſtly Sermon-makers ſhall cry, <hi>&amp;c. 11.</hi> Whited Walls proſeſſing nothing but poyſonous ſtuff. <hi>12.</hi> Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Wolves. <hi>13.</hi> Greedy Dogs; really they are Blood Hounds, ſtill hunting and gaſping after their prey like the mouth of Hell, barking and raging like <hi>Sodomites. 14.</hi> Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and ambitious Phariſees of the Devil; wo, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap> wo, was the portion of thoſe Phariſees then, and wo, wo, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>, is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Phariſees now; and wo and miſery is the portion of the Upholders (whether King or Parliament) of that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous and dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>itful generation.</p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>The Guide miſtaken,</hi> &amp;c. per W. Pen, <hi>p. 18:</hi> And whilſt the idle germundizing Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> run away with <hi>1500000l.</hi> a year, under preſence of being Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and that no ſort of people have been ſo u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>iverſally thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ugh ages the banc of ſoul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>nd body of the Univerſe, as that abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Tribe, for whom the Theatre of Gods m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ſt dreadful ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is reſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>d to act their eternal Tragedies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>pon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                 </div>
                                 <div type="part">
                                    <head>About Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ernors and Government.</head>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>Burrows Works,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 442.</hi> We believe that all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors and Rulers ought to be accountable to the people, and to the next ſucceeding Rulers, for all their actions which may be inquired into upon occaſion; and that the chiefeſt of the Rulers be ſubject under the Law, and puniſhable by it, if they be Tranſgreſſors, as well as the pooreſt of the people, <hi>p. 507.</hi> But as for this people [the Quakers] they are raiſed of the Lord, and eſtabliſhed by him <hi>even contrary to all men,</hi> and they have given their power only to God, and they cannot give their power to any mortal men, to ſtand or fall to any outward Authority, and to that they cannot ſeek, <hi>p. 501.</hi> We ſtand Witneſſes againſt Parliaments, Councels, Judges and Juſtices, who make and execute Laws in their wills ever the conſciences of men, to puniſh for conſcience ſake; to ſuch Laws, Cuſtoms, Courts, or arbitrary uſurped Dominion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap> cannot yeild obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46060:27"/> 
                                       <hi>p. 621.</hi> Nay their [the Quakers] Kingdom is from above, and they reject the countenance of the <hi>Beaſts autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and they reject any confidence that the Dragon and unjuſt power can repoſe in them, <hi>p. 53.</hi> For we (ſay the Quakers) are gathered up into the life which the holy men of God lived in, and are faln from the world, and its ways, and nature, <hi>p. 50.</hi> for even the <hi>Father</hi> bears witneſs of <hi>us,</hi> and therefore <hi>our</hi> witneſs is true, <hi>p. 52.</hi> A running to the powers of the earth? what have your Miniſters loſt the Lord to be your ſtrength that you muſt flee for help to men; <hi>muſt they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>aws to eſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>liſh you,</hi> and ſet you up; is not this the Where that rode upon the Beaſt, and that the Beaſt carried. <hi>And p. 524. to the Parliament thus,</hi> viz. You do but cauſe people to drink of the Whores Cup, and you are but them which carry the Whore, <hi>viz.</hi> the falſe Church; and this is plain dealing to tell you the truth, <hi>&amp;c. reprinted by the order and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>and others,</hi> Anno <hi>1672.</hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                       <hi>For more of this ſee</hi> Geo. Fox <hi>to the Councel of Officers, p. 7.</hi> Oh what a ſincerity was once in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; what <hi>a dirty unto</hi> thing it would have been to have heard talk of a Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ſe of Lords. <hi>Edw. Burroughs Advice to the Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. It was through Ignorance that the people ſubjected themſelves to hereditary Government, or to the Government ſtanding in a ſingle perſon ſucceſſively; and our Nation hath been under the bonds of ſlavery in this reſpest, <hi>&amp;c. See</hi> Fox's Papers to the Presbyterians, <hi>p. 8, 9.</hi> All Kings and Emperors have ſprung up in the night, ſince the days of the Apoſtles, among the Antichriſts. There was no King owned among the true Chriſtians, but only among the Apoſtates ſince Chriſts time. They were all Traytors againſt Chriſt that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired an earthly King. The true Chriſtians will not have any more Kings among them but Christ, <hi>&amp;c. News coming up out of the North</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 18.</hi> Dreadful is the Lord and powerful, who is coming to execute true judgment upon all you Judges, and to change all your Laws. Ye Kings, all you Rulers muſt down and ceaſe, and all you underling Officers which have been as the Arms of this great Tree; all your branches muſt be cut down, for you have been the fruitleſs branches grown on the fruitleſs tree, <hi>p. 19.</hi> ſo you muſt be cut down with the ſame power that cut down the King who reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over the Nation, whoſe Family was a Nurſery for Papiſts, and for Biſhops which held up Railes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> VVo, wo, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you all, the ſame Teachers are ſtanding that were in the time of the King, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap> ſame that were in the time of the Biſhops; ſuch as take Tythes: you muſt both be tormented together, Beaſt and falſe Prophet,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46060:28"/> 
                                       <hi>P. 20.</hi> Sing all ye Saints and rejoyce, clap your hands and be glad, for the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> will reign, and the Government ſhall be taken from you pretended Rulers, Judges and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Lawyers and Conſtables; all this Tree muſt be cut down, and Jeſus Chriſt [in us] will rule alone, <hi>p. 27.</hi> Sound the trumpet, ſound an alarm, call up to the battel, gather together for the deſtruction, draw the ſword, hew down all fruitleſs trees which cumber the ground, hew down all the powers of the earth, ſlay <hi>Baal;</hi> all the hirelings muſt be turned out of the kingdom, <hi>p. 35.</hi> All you who receive Tythes deny that Chriſt is come to us in the fleſh, <hi>p. 38.</hi> And thou beaſt and falſe Prophet muſt into the fire; the falſe Prophet is the Councellor to the Beaſt, and the Beaſt maintains the falſe Prophet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> E. Burroughs <hi>Declar.</hi> p. <hi>33. Upon a Rumour that the Quakers Meetings were to be broken up they writ,</hi> viz. Theſe Tydings do not trouble us, neither are we thereby moved; no, not to beg of any man (or men) the contrary, <hi>p. 40.</hi> and to any outward Authority we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſeek.</p>
                                 </div>
                                 <closer>
                                    <dateline>Mildenhall, <date>
                                          <hi>25th of</hi> Feb. <hi>1695.</hi>
                                       </date>
                                    </dateline>
                                    <signed>Fr. Bugg, Senior.</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                              <div n="christian" type="part">
                                 <p>We acknowledge and believe the Canonical Books of the Old and New Teſtament to be the moſt certain Rule of our Faith; and that not ſo much for the common conſent of the Church, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and perſwaſion of the Holy Ghoſt. And we believe that the doctrine contained in the holy Scriptures proceeds from God; from whom <hi>only,</hi> and not from men, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives its authority: And foraſmuch as it is the Rule of all Truth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining all matters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily required for the worſhip of God, and our Salvation, it is in no wiſe lawful for Men nor Angels to add unto, or take from this doctrine, or to change it: And hereupon it followeth, that it is not lawful to oppoſe either Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, or Cuſtom, or Multitude, or humane Wiſdom, Judgments, Edicts, or Decrees, or
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46060:26"/> Councils, or Viſions, or Miracles, unto this holy Scripture; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that all things ought to be examined and tried by the Rules and Square thereof; wherefore we do for this cauſe allow of thoſe three Creeds, namely the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the <hi>Nicene,</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Creed; becauſe they be agreeable to the Word of God. We believe that all the Off-ſpring of <hi>Adam</hi> are infected with Original Sin, which is a vice hereditary to us by propagation; and not only by imitations, as the <hi>Pelagians</hi> aſſert, whoſe errors are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by us: we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this ſtain of Original Sin is Sin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; howbeit, they that are the Children of God ſhall never be condemned for it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God of his rich grace and mercy doth not impute it to them; but out of his bounty doth deliver them through our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Jeſus Chriſt, being the Wiſdom, and Eternal Son of God, took upon him our Nature, ſo that he is one perſon God and man; man that he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46060:26"/> might be able to ſuffer in ſoul and body; made like unto us in all things, ſin only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; ſo that as to hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ne nature he was indeed the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of <hi>David,</hi> conceived in due time in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> by the ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>et and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible power of the Holy Ghoſt; and that in one and the ſame perſon, to wit, the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>rd Jeſus Chriſt; his two natures are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably conjoined and united; yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in ſuch a manner, that each nature doth retain its diſtinct pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; ſo that even as in this divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, the divine Nature retaining its properties doth ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide uncreated, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and filling all places; ſo alſo the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth finite, having form, meaſure and property. And alſo the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt when he roſe from the dead gave Immortality to his body, yet he never deprived it of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of its nature: therefore we do ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Chriſt in his Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as that we do not rob him of his Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46060:27"/> We believe that by that one Sacrifice which Jeſus Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered upon the Croſs we are reconciled unto God, that ſo we may be accounted righteous in his ſight. And we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Jeſus Chriſt is conferred upon us to be our alone Advocate; and that he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in our prayers to preſent our ſelves to the Father in his name. We do alſo reject thoſe means which derogate from the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of the <hi>death</hi> and <hi>paſſion</hi> of our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And we believe where the word of God is not received, and where there is <hi>no uſe</hi> of <hi>Sacrame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ts,</hi> we cannot judge that there is any Church; for we believe that the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are <hi>abſolued</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>word</hi> that they may be pledges and tokens of the Grace of God. We believe that God will have the world ruled by Laws, and Civil Government, that there may be ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap> ſort of bridles by which the unruly luſts of the world may be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and that therefore he appointeth Kings and Commonwealths, and other kinds of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, whether he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46060:27"/> or otherwiſe; and not that alone, but alſo what pertaineth to the Miniſtration of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, whereof he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth himſelf to be the Author; therefore hath he de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ivered the Sword into the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates hands, that ſo ſins committed againſt both Tables of Gods Law, not only againſt the ſecond, but firſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may be ſuppreſſed; and therefore becauſe God is the Author of this order, we muſt not only ſuffer Magiſtrates whom he hath ſet over us, but we muſt alſo give them much Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Reverence, as unto his Officers and Lieutenants which have received their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from him to exerciſe ſo lawful and ſacred a Function; therefore we affirm, that Obedience muſt be yielded unto their Laws, that Tribute and Taxes muſt be paid, and the Yoak of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection born, although the Magiſtrates be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels, ſo that the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Government of God be preſerved; wherefore we do deteſt all thoſe who do reject the higher powers.</p>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="printers_advertisment">
            <head>BOoks written by <hi>Fr. Bugg, Sen.</hi> as followeth, ſome of which are intended to be bound together and ſold, as on the Title Page; whereby ſuch as deſire further ſatisfaction into the nature of the Controverſy, may inform themſelves.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>De Chriſtianae Libertate,</hi> in <hi>Octavo,</hi> bound.</item>
               <item>II. The Painted Harlot both ſtript and whipt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. Reaſon againſt Rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and Truth againſt Falſhood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. Innocency vindicated, and Envy rebuked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. The Quakers detected, and their Errors confuted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. A Letter to the Quakers, ſhewing their frequent addreſſing to the late <hi>K. J.</hi> and their never addreſſing his preſent Majeſty.</item>
               <item>VII. Battering Rams againſt New Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. One Blow more at New Rome, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IX. New Rome unmasked, and her Foundation ſhaken, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>X. New Rome arraigned, and out of her own Mouth condemned.</item>
               <item>XI. A Sheet delivered to the Parliament <hi>Dec.</hi> 93. intituled, Something in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Quakers Allegations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XII. Quakeriſm withering, and Chriſtianity reviving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XIII. Quakeriſm anatomized, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being a Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lenge to <hi>R. Aſhby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XIV. A Sheet intituled, The Quakers Yearly Meeting impeached, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XV. A Second Summons to the City <hi>Abel,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. by way of metaphor to deliver up <hi>Sheba</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri</hi> (i. e.) <hi>G. Whitehead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>XVI. The Quakers ſet in their true light.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 7. for <hi>Book</hi> read <hi>Books,</hi> l. 28. for <hi>Book</hi> r. <hi>Books,</hi> p. 5. l. 4. for <hi>White</hi> r. <hi>Whitehead,</hi> p. 7. l. 26. for <hi>ot</hi> r. <hi>not,</hi> p. 11. l. 23 and 24. for <hi>troop</hi> r. <hi>trooper,</hi> p 12. l. 42. for <hi>Iſays</hi> r. <hi>Jays,</hi> p. 21. l. 17. for <hi>of him</hi> r. <hi>of truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46060:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
